<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pagan prince, or, A comical history of the heroick atchievements of the Palatine of Eboracum by the author of the Secret history of King Charles II and K. James II.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54442</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12017438</idno>
  <idno type="VID">52570</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942721</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2982</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12017438</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 573:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pagan prince, or, A comical history of the heroick atchievements of the Palatine of Eboracum by the author of the Secret history of King Charles II and K. James II.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 144.</note>
                  <note>A satire on James, Duke of York, later James II.</note>
                  <note>Pages 131-134 are missing in filmed copy. Pages 126-end photographed from University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:1"/>
            <p>THE Pagan Prince: Or a Comical History OF THE Heroick Atchievements OF THE Palatine of <hi>Eboracum</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Author of the Secret History of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. and K. <hi>James</hi> II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amsterdam.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:2"/>
            <head>TO THE French King.</head>
            <p>BEhold, Great Sir, a Champion of your own moulding; and tho' not altogether of the growth, yet the perfect Manufacture of <hi>France.</hi> For in your Court he had his Education, and learnt his first Rudiments of War, under one of your greatest Generals, who God rest his Soul, was curs'd in his Mothers belly, as being kill'd with a Cannon Bullet, upon the Dry Land. 'Tis true, that once upon a time, you felt to your sorrow, the puissance of this are adful Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions Arm; but that Brush being over, and all things reconcil'd, he has ever since most Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially and Strenuously fought all along for your Interest and Exaltation. He abandon'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of his Fathers, and Embrac'd the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of his Mothers to make you Great, aad run through Fire and Water to serve your turns: and I humbly submit it to your incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judgment whether those two Elements, as your Champion managed them, did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb facs="tcp:52570:3"/> very much to the Advancement of your Great Designs. These things you consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, and told him that your Interest and his were so clearly link'd together, that they who oppos'd the one should be look't upon as Enemies to the other. Vouchsafe then Great Sir, kindly to entertain him, returning to your Country laden with Renown and the Spoils of your Enemies; and if not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of his Immortal Exploites, yet for the sake of his and your most beloved <hi>Messa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina,</hi> bestow upon him one Corner of the Vast Pasty of your Conquests, for him to rest his Limbs grown Old and Enfeebl'd with the Toyls and Hardships of those many Combats which he has undertaken in your Quarrel. Such a Grateful Generosity will oblige both us and all your Votaries to pray, that your Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses for the future may be all like his, and that you may prosper in all your enterprizes as hitherto he has done.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHap. 1. <hi>Of his Education in his Younger Years.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>Of certain remarkable Passages that foretold his future Grandeur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>How the two Princes of</hi> Naceleor, <hi>and the Duke of</hi> Longvisage, <hi>came to visit the young Palatine, and of the Learned Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course that pass'd between them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>Of the Remarkable Decision which the Palatine made of one of the difficultest Causes in the World.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 5. <hi>How the Sieur</hi> Richard Roe <hi>pleaded his cause before the</hi> Palatine <hi>in answer to the Sieur</hi> John Doe.</item>
               <item>Chap. 6. <hi>How the Palatine decided this Great and Difficult Cause in the Twinkling of an Eye.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>Of the various discourses at Dinner,
<pb facs="tcp:52570:4"/> and how the Palatine made a particular Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course upon Valour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 8. <hi>Of the Pleasant discourse which the Palatine and the two Princes had after Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>How the two</hi> Astopian <hi>Princes took their leaves of the Palatine, and the Palatine of them, and what follow'd thereupon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>How the</hi> Astopians <hi>robb'd the</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian <hi>Bakers of their Buns; and of the Cruel Wars that ensu'd between the two Kings of</hi> Astopia <hi>and</hi> Arragonian Belgium.</item>
               <item>Chap. 11. <hi>How the Marshal of</hi> Tonneure <hi>was made Chief Commander of the</hi> Astopian <hi>Army, who chose the Palatine of</hi> Eboracum <hi>to be General of his Horse.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 12. <hi>Of the Great Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>parations which the Palatine made, and of the Discourse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and an Armourer about the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of his Arms.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ch. 13. <hi>Of his Discourse with his Page about being invulnerable.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 14. <hi>Now comes his Conference with</hi> Vulcan <hi>the Armourer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 15. <hi>How a certain Doctor came to the Palatine and prescrib'd him a Diet to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease his Courage.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 16. <hi>Of the wonderful Atchievements which the Palatine performed in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of General of the Horse.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:52570:4"/>
               <item>Chap. 17. <hi>How the Palatine was Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented out of</hi> Astopia, <hi>and of something else beside.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 18. <hi>Of one of the strangest things that ever happen'd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 19. <hi>How the</hi> Palatine <hi>was entertain'd by the Governour of</hi> Belgic-Arragonia; <hi>and how he vow'd to be reveng'd upon the</hi> Astopians.</item>
               <item>Chap. 20. <hi>Of the Great War between the</hi> Astopians <hi>and the</hi> Belgic-Arragonians; <hi>where you may probably hear of something which the Palatine did to his Eternal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 21. <hi>How the</hi> Palatine <hi>was restor'd to his</hi> Palatinate <hi>in</hi> Albion, <hi>and how he rode Tantivy to</hi> Papimania.</item>
               <item>Chap. 22. <hi>Of the great Herring War between the</hi> Belgians <hi>and the</hi> Albionians, <hi>and how the Palatine was made</hi> Archithalassus <hi>of</hi> Albion.</item>
               <item>Chap. 23. <hi>Of the Great Preparations which the Palatine made to fight the</hi> Belgians.</item>
               <item>Chap. 24. <hi>Of the desperate engagement between the</hi> Belgians <hi>and the</hi> Albionians, <hi>and of the undaunted courage of the Palatine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 25. <hi>Being a Continuation of things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to be left out.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 26. <hi>Of the most terrible Engagement
<pb facs="tcp:52570:5"/> that ever was upon the face of the Sea, and how valorously the Palatine behav'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 27. <hi>Being a Continuation of the Bloody Engagement.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 28. <hi>Of the Miraculous Preservation of the Palatine, which surpasses all belief.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 29. <hi>How the Palatine wak'd and was found again to the great Joy of those that beheld him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ch. 30. <hi>Of the Great Rejoycing and Triumphing in the City of</hi> Troy-Novant, <hi>for the great Victory obtain'd against the</hi> Belgians, <hi>and of the great Honours done the</hi> Palatine.</item>
               <item>Chap. 31. <hi>How Peace ensu'd, and then War, and then Peace and then War again between the</hi> Albionians <hi>and the</hi> Belgians, <hi>and how the Palatine cut the Gordian Knot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 32. <hi>How the Palatine follow'd the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of</hi> Nero <hi>the Tyrant of</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>Chap. 33. <hi>More of this and something else.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 34. <hi>Of the Great Similitude in every particular between the</hi> Two <hi>dismal Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grations of Old</hi> Rome <hi>and</hi> New Troy.</item>
               <item>Chap. 35. <hi>Where the Comparison ends.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 36. <hi>Of the Great joy at the Imperial Court of</hi> Gehenna <hi>for the Burning of</hi> Troy-Novant <hi>and how the King of</hi> Astopia <hi>and the</hi> Palatine <hi>triumph'd over a Map of the Ruines.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:52570:5"/>
               <item>Chap. 37. <hi>How the</hi> Palatine <hi>and the King of</hi> Astopia <hi>pursu'd their design of destroying the</hi> Belgians.</item>
               <item>Chap. 38. <hi>How the Palatine set the</hi> Albio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians <hi>and the</hi> Belgians <hi>a third time together by the Ears, by a Wile.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 39. <hi>How the Palatine pursu'd his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs against the</hi> Belgians.</item>
               <item>Chap. 40. <hi>Of the Great Preparations which the</hi> Palatine <hi>made to Encounter the</hi> Belgians <hi>a Third time.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 41. <hi>How the Palatine went to seek out the</hi> Belgians, <hi>but found 'em not, and of his Resolutions thereupon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 42. <hi>Of the great perplexity the Palatine was in.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 43. <hi>Of something worth your Hearing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 44. <hi>How the</hi> Palatine <hi>was surpriz'd by the</hi> Belgians, <hi>and how he sacrific'd his Vice-Archithalassus, the Knight of the Pointed Mount to his Despair.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 45. <hi>How the Palatine wrested the Victory out of the</hi> Belgians <hi>hands, and of the Great Bon-fire he made for joy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 46. <hi>Of the Noise which the Palatines great Atchievements made in the far distant Regions of the World, and the various Effects of it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 47. <hi>How the Palatine marry'd the most
<pb facs="tcp:52570:6"/> Beautiful</hi> Messalina <hi>Princess of</hi> Demonia <hi>upon the River</hi> Eridanus, <hi>with whom he had a Golden Mountain, and</hi> Phaetons <hi>Reliques for her Portion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 48. <hi>How the Palatine, the more to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate himself with his new marry'd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, rais'd the numerous Band of the</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flambs <hi>of</hi> Troy-novant, <hi>and how he encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and overthrew the whole Army of the</hi> Chinabeefians, Costardi, <hi>and</hi> Vensonpastig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians, <hi>three great Nations in perpetual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with the Albionians, upon the Plains of</hi> Drappers-hallia.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52570:6"/>
            <head>CHAP. 1. Of his Education in his Younger Years.</head>
            <p>THE Palatine of <hi>Eboracum</hi> and <hi>Albania,</hi> was brought up at <hi>Lutetia</hi> in <hi>Astopia,</hi> where he had a Tutor provided him by his Mother, who in his younger Years, that is to say, from Three to Five, taught him to Drink, Eat, and Sleep; to Eat, Sleep and Drink, and to Sleep, Drink and Eat. After that, he taught him to catch Flies and run after Butterflies; to Piss upon his Shoes, to sh—in his Shirt, and wipe his Nose upon his Sleeve, to wash his hands in his Porridge, to sit between two stools till his Breech came to the ground, to colour ill Dealings with bad Pretences, to eat dry Bread for want of other Victuals, to hide himself in the water from the Rain, to toil to little purpose, to answer quite from the Matter, to strike a Dog before a Lion: to put the Cart before the Horse, to scratch where it never itch'd, to eat his Whitebread first, to trifle away time, to flatter himself with fond Imaginations, to reckon without his Host, to beat the Bush and lose the Birds, to believe the Moon was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52570:7"/> made of green Cheese, to take Bladders for Lanthorns, to hope to catch Larks when the Sky fell, and to make a Vertue of Necessity.</p>
            <p>With these Instructions, the young Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine grew up into such hopes, that his Mother was ravish'd with Admiration to behold the extraordinary Wit and Apprehension of her young Son. Quo she, I find in this Son of mine, a Genius aspiring to Divinity it self, so sharp, so subtle, so profound, so clear is his Apprehension. Quo she, He told me t'other day, the prettiest Story of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, I wonder i' my heart where he had it! He told me that <hi>Alexander</hi> had a Horse so fierce and fiery that no body durst ride him, he had thrown three or four Riders one after the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he had broken the Neck of one, the Legs of another, and beat out the brains and all the Teeth of a fourth. But <hi>Alexander</hi> found it out, that, the true reason why the Horse was so furious was; for that he was frighted with his own shadow: <hi>Alexander</hi> therefore getting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Back, rode him directly against the Sun, so that the shadow was always behind, and by that means in a little time so tam'd the Horse, that he became as gentle as a Lamb. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon another Tutor was sought for more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for his Years; and at last they found out an old <hi>Sophister,</hi> whose Name was <hi>Tubal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofernes,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52570:7"/> who first taught him his Horn-Book so exactly, that he could say it by heart back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. So that his Tutor seeing him run so prodigiously fast (for he had learnt both this and his Primmer in five Years and three Months) began to read to him several other Authors of greater moment; as the Book of <hi>The Seven Champions,</hi> Palmerin <hi>of</hi> England, Belianis <hi>of</hi> Greece, Don Quixot, <hi>and The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend of Captain</hi> Jones: and in these Studies he spent thirteen Years, six Months, and a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night just. But his Mother being a Lady of great Devotion in the Pagan Religion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signing the young Palatine to be of the same Belief, Pious toward the Pagan Deities and Saints, as well as valiant Champion for the Cause, order'd his Tutor to imprint in his royal Mind her own Principles in Matters of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Faith. To which purpose, <hi>Holofernes</hi> made him a diligent Hearer of <hi>Scotus, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin, Suarez, Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and the rest of that Gang: And to render those crabbed Authors the more delightful, sometime he read to the young Palatine himself in private, the Spanish <hi>Celestina, Aretine</hi>'s Dialogues, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of his Grandfather by the Mother's side, together with <hi>Petronius Arbiter,</hi> and <hi>Martial</hi>'s Epigrams, that the young Prince might be <hi>tam Mercurio quam Marti.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52570:8"/>
            <p>After that, this Tutor dy'd of a Clap which he got in his Old Age, and the Palatine was put under the care of <hi>Ponocrates;</hi> who order'd Him to rise every Morning between Eight &amp; Nine of the Clock, whether it were day or no; then to put on his Cloaths, which he generally co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with a large thick frize Coat, lin'd with Fox Skins; then to Comb his Head with a <hi>German Comb,</hi> that is to say, his four Fingers and Thumb. For his Tutor told him, That▪ to comb, wash, and finifie himself any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, was but to waste time in this world. After that he was order'd methodically to evacuate as well by Stool as Urin, to break wind, hauk, spit, hickup, sneeze, and so to Breakfast, which was generally upon good <hi>Westphalia</hi> Hamms, Carbonadoes, cold Chicken or Partridges with Oyl and Vinegar, or fat Brewis to keep out the Infections of the Air. 'Tis true, <hi>Ponocrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> told him, 'twas not wholsom for him to Eat so soon after he was up, before he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd some Exercise. How so? said the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; Have I not rowl'd and tumbl'd in my Bed at least six or seven times before I get up Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> did so, by the Advice of the Jew his Physitian, and liv'd till he dy'd in spite of all the world.</p>
            <p>After Breakfast, he went to Church, carrying along with him in a large Pannier, a huge Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viary,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52570:8"/> weighing Cover and Parchment, and all little less than Eleven hundred and six Pounds. There he heard about Six and twenty or thirty Masses. And at the same time came to him a Mumbler of Orisons, with his Chin muffl'd up like the <hi>Whooping Bird,</hi> with whom he mutter'd over all his <hi>Kyrie Eleyson</hi>'s, more than sixteen Hermits could have said i'th' time.</p>
            <p>This done, he went to Dinner upon some Dozens of Hamms, Neats Tongues, Herring, Saucidges, and such other Vancurriers of Wine while four Men stood ready to throw in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard into his Mouth by shovel fulls, to make him tast his Liquor, which was a hideous draught of Whitewine to comfort his Kidneys.</p>
            <p>But this was no more than a Wine Cooper could have done; and therefore <hi>Ponocrates</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to give his young Pupil more Princely Education. To which purpose, the famous <hi>Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastes</hi> was sent for, and entertain'd in Pay, to teach the young Palatine to ride the great Horse. Every morning therefore he was mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, sometimes upon a Barb, sometimes upon a Genet; and a fine Sight it was to see him some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times curvetting in the Air, at another time either leaping Ditches, or taking Pales or a high Wall, that his Horse could but just lay his Nose over. At another time, I cannot say he was for breaking his Launce; for that's the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52570:9"/> idlest thing i'the world to say, I have broken ten Launces at a Tilting, or in a Battle; any Carpenter might say as much: but the honour lyes in breaking ten Launces of the Enemy with one of his own. His business therefore was with a stiff Iron-cheek'd Launce at one time to pierce a Coat of Armour, throw down a Tree, or upon the point of it to carry away a great Saddle, a Halbert or a Gauntlet, and this too all in compleat Armour himself from head to foot: and then for the <hi>Pop</hi> and <hi>Smack</hi> to encourage his Horse, there was no man could compare with him. The Curvetter of <hi>Ferrara</hi> was but an Ape in comparison of him; he would leap out of one Saddle into another without alighting: and with his Launce in his fist, when upon the Ground, would mount his Courser without Bridle or Stirrups, and guide him as he listed. He wrestl'd, run and leap'd to admiration. He made nothing of a Ditch ten paces wide: he would run six paces up a steep Wall, and clamber up to a Window ten foot high. He would run up a Tree like a Cat, and leap from Bough to Bough like a Squirrel. And which was more, with two strong steel Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and two strong Bodkins he would run up to the top of a House like a Rat, and come down again without ever hurting himself. And by such Exercises as these, he inur'd himself
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52570:9"/> in such a manner to Military Labours, that he won himself the fame of being one of the most hardy and hopeful Knights in all <hi>Astopia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Of certain remarkable Passages that foretold his future Grandeur.</head>
            <p>WHile he was thus under Tutelage, it happen'd that he went in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time into the Country, partly to take the Air, and partly to learn the way of seeking Forrest Adventures, after the manner of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Champions, of whom he resolv'd to be an exact Imitator. And it is reported, that he was so enrag'd against one Forrest for harbouring Hornets and Gadbee's to the great persecution of his Horses Buttocks as he rode along, that had he not been mollify'd by his Tutors, who told him he might do what he pleas'd in his own Territories, but that he had nothing to do there, he would not have left a Tree stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but would have grubb'd up the Elms and Oaks with his hands, till he had laid the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest as bare as the Downs of <hi>Sarum.</hi> However this great and magnanimous resolution of his to revenge his Horses Buttocks, had spread it self far and near; so that when he return'd back to <hi>Lutetia,</hi> Heaven's! how the people throng'd in heaps to see him. Some in Admiration of his growing fame, others expecting he would
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52570:10"/> have set all the Conduits a running Wine, to give them his welcom to Town. But as he rode along, the Multitude and Press of the Rabble was so extraordinary, that he was forc'd to step from his Saddle into one of the Towers of the Temple of <hi>Nosterdamus.</hi> Where being at a little Ease, and seeing the vast Clusters of People underneath him; I'le lay my Life, quo he, these Ragamuffins expect that I should give 'em my welcom home: If I do, quo he, it shall be in Wine of my own Burning; and so saying, he let go from his <hi>Priapus</hi> with that frankness and generosity, that he drown'd no less than Thirty four thousand, four hundred and eighteen, besides Women and Children.</p>
            <p>They that escap'd the terrible shower, when they were got out of danger, sweating, cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, spitting, and quite out of breath all in hurly burly and confusion, some fell a Swearing and Cursing like so many Tinkers; others could not choose but laugh at the Conceit: quo they, if he fights as he pisses, it will not be the Great Turks best way to provoke him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52570:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ch. 3.</hi> How the two Princes of <hi>Naceleo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Longvisage,</hi> came to visit the young Palatine, and of the Learned Discourse that pass'd between them.</head>
            <p>BY this time the Palatine was arriv'd to years of Maturity; and had so improv'd himself in all Military Exercises, that he was become the Talk and wonder of all <hi>Astopia,</hi> Certainly, said the Prince of <hi>Naceleor</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Long visage,</hi> if what is reported of this <hi>Troynovan:</hi> Palatine be truth, he must be a Composition of all the Seven Champions toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thereupon they both resolv'd upon a day to give the Palatine a Visit, as well for that they thought it not fitting that such a Person should live in the world of <hi>Astopia,</hi> and they not know him, as also that they might be able to testifie upon their own Tryal the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of what otherwise s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em'd to be so strange and Romantick. Those two great <hi>Astopian</hi> Grandees were not ignorant how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent it is for Flatterers to cry up in great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages those Things for Perfections, which in others would be look'd upon as little Acquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. On the other side, they consider'd that Flattery attended only upon those that were able to reward; and therefore why men should take so much pains to extol the Palatine, who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52570:11"/> at that time had not a foot of Land in the whole Universe, they could not conceive. But then they reflected again, that they who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded him to that high degree, were men of foresight, and flatter'd him not for what he had at present, but believing that through his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and other extraordinary Endowments, he would not only purchase Kingdoms, but Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires hereafter. But because they would not go empty handed, in imitation of the Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian Queen to <hi>Solomon</hi> the Wise, they order'd their Squires to let the Palatine know their Intention beforehand, as being unwilling to surprize so great a Prince; and to make way for their own welcom, they provided a <hi>Regalio</hi> or Present consisting of seventeen Oxen, three Heifers, two and thirty Calves, sixty three fat Kids, fourscore and fifteen Weathers, three hundred sucking Pigs, eleven score pair of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges, seven hundred Woodcocks, four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fat Capons, six thousand Pullets, and as many Pigeons, six hundred Phesants, fourteen hundred Leverets, three hundred and three Bustards, and one thousand seven hundred Cock-chickens: How many Haunches of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nison I cannot presently reckon; besides eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen fat Bucks that were sent by the <hi>Lord the Lord knows who.</hi> Wildfowls there were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number, as Teal, Widgins, Plovers, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wits,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52570:11"/> Lapwings, More-hens, Herons, with seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others, for which we have no names. And that there might be no want of all the choicest &amp; rarest Wines that <hi>Astopia</hi> could afford, there was Provision made of no less than two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd and six Hampers, each Hamper contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twelve Dozen of Bottles. With this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the two Squires being sent before, deliver'd their Message with a decency answerable to the Dignity of their Masters from whom they came, and the Sublimity of the Palatine, to whom they were sent. The Palatine on the other side admiring the Magnificence of the Present, receiv'd the two Squires with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Civility and Affability, and after he had slipp'd into each of their right hands a French half Crown, assur'd them of his great acknowledgment of the signal Honour which their Masters had done him, and how glad he should be of their good Company. Presently seven thousand six hundred fifty four Cooks were set to work to prepare and dress this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful heap of Varieties, besides Scullions and Turn-broaches: And the Palatine took care that every thing was done with that extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Method and Sobriety, as denoted the exactness of his future O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>conomy and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: insomuch that because the Chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Knives should not make too much noise,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52570:12"/> the very Dresser-Boards were lin'd with dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bays.</p>
            <p>And now the Day appointed being come, the two <hi>Astopian</hi> Peers appear'd with their Trains so numerous and magnificent, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be said to equal them, unless the ancient Trains of the Kings of <hi>Persia;</hi> or that of the <hi>Great Mogul,</hi> when he goes abroad to visit his Elephants. When they enter'd into the Great Hall, they found the Palatine hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a very difficult and perplex'd Cause, that had puzzl'd all the Courts and all the Great Lawyers of <hi>Astopia,</hi> so that the two Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists being quite tir'd with the Delays and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of the Law, resolv'd to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves for his determination to the Palatine, of whose piercing Wit and quick Apprehension they had heard so loud a Character.</p>
            <p>The Cause was a very knotty Cause be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sieur <hi>John Doe</hi> Plaintiff, and the Sieur <hi>Richard Roe</hi> Defendant. By the way, I should have told ye, that when the Palatine saw the two Princes enter, he would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended from his Judgment Seat to meet them; but they cry'd out to him, No, no, Sir <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> no by no means, go on with your Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: which they were the rather willing to do, in regard they came not as Taylors to take measure of his Body, but of his Soul; which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52570:12"/> they knew could no way better be done than by observation of the Acuteness of his Wit and Judgment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Of the Remarkable Decision which the Palatine made of one of the difficultest Causes in the World.</head>
            <p>NOw the Case was this. The Sieur <hi>John Doe</hi> Plaintiff, pleaded, that a certain old Woman belonging to his House, carri'd a Basket of Eggs to Market to sell. Now this Woman stept aside between the two Tropics six Inches toward the <hi>Zenith,</hi> because the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaean</hi> Mountains that year were very barren of Kickshaws, by reason of a terrible Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between the Gibble Gabblers, and your Men of Brevity, who both argu'd for the Rebellion of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> who were assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl'd together like flies in a Sugar Chest to go about with their Wassail-bowls just at the time of the Year, when People first begin to give their Cows Porridge, and their Dogs Oats. But the Physicians affirm'd, they found no reason by her Urine, but that the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man might eat Iron Mattocks with Mustard, unless it were that the great Men at Court had forbidden the French Disease to trouble the Bumpkins, as being more desirous to entertain it themselves. Nevertheless who would not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52570:13"/> let go the Bird before he be troubled, and have his Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s cufft to make him discover it. For there is no reason, why <hi>Lent</hi> falls so high, but that <hi>Easter</hi> never comes, but it costs a man money.</p>
            <p>Here the Sieur <hi>Richard Roe</hi> interrupting the Sieur <hi>John Doe,</hi> by the Belly of St. <hi>Anthony, quo</hi> the <hi>Palatine,</hi> what have you to do to speak before your time? I sweat here like a Wine-Porter to understand your Business, and you must be perplexing the Cause—Hold your Tongue in the Devils name, and speak when it comes to your turn.</p>
            <p>Then the Sieur <hi>John Doe</hi> proceeding, Sir, said he, when I saw that the Pragmatick San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made nothing of this matter, but that the Pope gave Liberty for every one to fart at their own Pleasure, let them be as poor as they would, provided the Blankets were whole, and considering that there was a Rain-bow ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd at <hi>Rome</hi> lately, to give notice to the People to hatch Larks; a kinsman of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans perswaded her, since the Pope and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were agreed, to discharge her <hi>Ischiatics,</hi> and not to put her self to the pain of hiding the perturbation of her body. Now I being willing to obey the King, arm'd my self from top to toe with good B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly timber, to see how my Vintagers had pink'd their Steeple Crown'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52570:13"/> Caps, that they might the better be able to play at <hi>In, and In;</hi> thô it were a dangerous time, considering that several of the Guards were refus'd Mustring, for wearing black patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es upon their Noses. Therefore it was like to be a good year for Tawny-beetles to the great ease of the Carriers of Pardons, when they have eaten till their Bellies Crack with their Breeches unbutton'd. These things consider'd without any more Niceties or slicing of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, I desire your Lordships opinion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Case and Allowance of my Expences, with Interest and Dammages.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> How the Sieur <hi>Richard Roe</hi> pleaded his cause before the <hi>Palatine</hi> in answer to the Sieur <hi>John Doe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THen the Sieur <hi>Richard Roe</hi> taking his turn, My Lord and Right Worshipful, if the Iniquity of men were but as easily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd by plain Authentical Judgment, as we discern flies in Milk, the World as to the four Oxen, would not be so much eaten up with Rats as it is. For thô what my Adversary has said be very true as to the Letter and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of the <hi>Factum,</hi> yet the little Tricks, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and Cavils of the Law are hidden under the Cloak for the Knavery.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, I bought a Curtal of <hi>High Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52570:14"/> of a very good Wool, and dy'd in Grain, as the Goldsmiths assur'd me, but the Notary put in other things. I am no Clerk to take the Moon by the Horns with my Teeth, but at the Butter Pot, where the Instruments were seal'd, the report was, that salt Beef would make a man find out the Wine thô 'twere hid at the bottom of a Charcoal mans Sack. I have consulted great Clerks and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers about this matter, and they all conclude, that there is no such way in the World as dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all the Summer long in a Cave well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd with Pen, Ink and Paper: For as soon as the Harness smells of Garlick, the rust eats away the Liver of it. <hi>Tarabin Tarabas.</hi> 'Tis true, that as to the four Oxen, concerning which the Dispute is, their Memories were somewhat short; but as to the Knowledge of their Gammut, they defi'd all the Canary Birds in the Country. For grant that upon coupling of two Grey-hounds, the Puppies should grow proud before their Time, with Submission to the Court, it does not thence follow that six Acres of Land, at full measure shall amount to three Vessels of fine Ink, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blowing in the Bason; that is, without pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down ready Money, and so I pray your Highnesses Judgment with allowance of Costs, Dammages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52570:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> How the Palatine decided this Great and Difficult Cause in the Twinckling of an Eye.</head>
            <p>THe Defendant having thus made an end, the Palatine demanded of the Sieur <hi>John Doe,</hi> whether he had any thing to reply? Who answering, <hi>No,</hi> the Palatine turning to the Counsellors and Doctors there assembled, you have heard, said he, the Case argu'd, and now what think you of it? <hi>Yes</hi> quo they, an't please you Sir, we have heard it, but the Devil a bit do we understand it. Well says the Palatine, then I'le make an end of it, for I can find no such difficulty in it, as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. Hearken therefore to the Sentence of the Court which is this. The Court having considered the horrible shuddering of the <hi>Flick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouse</hi> in her brave retreat from the Summer Solstice, to court the <hi>Kickshaws</hi> of the Age that were got Sick of the Pip with their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights debauchery, so that the good Woman was frighted from her Marketing by that same Hypocrite of an <hi>Archer,</hi> that stands al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with his Bow bent in the sky; and forc'd to walk with her Feet swell'd, one Stoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin off and t'other on, therefore the Plaintiff has just cause of Complaint; and therefore in Conscience the good Woman ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imburs'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52570:15"/> in Gew-gaws to the full number of the Hairs upon the Heifers back; and so much for the Embroiderer, that is to say, so much for that. The Plaintiff is also discharg'd from all Royal Prosecutions upon any Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for not having made all clean after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneration, as was fairly decided by two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumers upon a fair Tryal of his Bum▪ Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot levell'd exactly at a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udle of Wallnuts. Only because the Plaintiff has charg'd the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant to be a Cobler, a Runaway, and a Clipper of Money, which after long Jangling and Wrangling the Plaintiff has not prov'd, the Court condemns him in three large pair of Drawers full of Cheese-curds well press'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Gingembob'd and Cod-piec'd after the fashion of the Countrey, payable to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant every <hi>Mid-August</hi> in <hi>May.</hi> On the other side, the Defendant shall be oblig'd to furnish the Plaintiff with Hay and Tow to open the passage of his Gut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ural Trap doors, when ever they shall be pester'd with any Fat Morsels that are ready to choak him: and so to be good Friends as before.</p>
            <p>This decree was look't upon as a thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond imagination. For it never happen'd since the Flood, nor ever will happen in thirteen Jubiles, that two Persons so long at Daggers drawing as <hi>John Doe</hi> and <hi>Rich. Roe</hi> had been,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52570:15"/> were ever so satisfi'd with a decree as those two Adversaries were. As for the Counsellors and Doctors that were present, they were all in an Extasie for three hours together; and some of 'em were in such an amaze that they were forc'd to throw Rose-water and Vinegar in their faces to fetch 'em again. And as for the two Princes they sate staring upon one another, like two strange Cats in Admiration that a Person so young as the <hi>Palatine</hi> should be able to understand the Laws and Customs of <hi>Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> better than all the most learned Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors and Judges of the Land. With that the two Princes rose up and embraced the <hi>Palatine</hi> with all the Tenderness imaginable; wishing him withal, according to his deserts, the Early command of a Kingdom, which certainly they said, must be the most happy in the World under the Government of such a Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and Prudent Prince. On the other side the Palatine begg'd their Pardon for having made them tarry so long, but hop'd they would make themselves amends by that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which they had made their undoubted Right and due through their unparallell'd Bounty and Magnificence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52570:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Of the various discourses at Dinner, and how the Palatine made a particular Discourse upon Valour.</head>
            <p>DInner being serv'd up, all that were to sit down, took their places; and they that were to wait, stood upon their feet, as is usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al upon such occasions. Now as the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was numerous, and every one had the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to use his Freedom, so it were within the Limits of Decency and Descretion, hence it was that the greatest part of the Task was only Rimble ramble D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>scourse. Among the rest there was a good Jolly Priest, I have forgot what his name was, who by his Nose seem'd to be much more fond of officiating at a good Feast, than at the Altar; and by his Habit seem'd to be some <hi>Pagan, Abbot,</hi> or Arch <hi>Flamin</hi> of the Pagan order of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> but what ever he was, his tongue seldom lay still, and he set other mens tongues a going as fast as his own. There was not a dish of Meat that came to the Table, but he had something to comment upon it. Quo he, of all the Fish that swim in Salt or Fresh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, except it be a Tench, give me the Wing of a Partridge, or the Thigh of a <hi>Nun,</hi> and by my consent he shall never be look't upon as a good fellow that dyes with an empty Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52570:16"/>
               <hi>Quo</hi> the Prince of <hi>Naceleor,</hi> I know one of your Coat, that always commanded the White of a Capon. That's quite contrary to the Judgment of your Foxes, cry'd another, for they still leave the white of Poultry, and yet one would think they should be the best judges of the Brawn of a Capon. Oh, quo the <hi>Flamin,</hi> that's because your Foxes have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cooks nor Kitchins. For if Poultry be not well boil'd, their flesh will look red and not white. The redness of Victuals is a sign of rawness: except it be in Lobsters and Cray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fish, for those the more they look like Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, the better they are. And is that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, honest Priest, quo the D. of <hi>Longvisage,</hi> that ye rank the <hi>Thighs</hi> of a Nun, with the Wing of a Partridge? No, no, my Lord, but because they say that part is the best which always exercises most: and therefore we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Legs of Tame fowl, before the Wings of Wild foul. But to the purpose, Page bring me a Brimmer,—so—now have at that Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, there's no Malice against the dead. 'Tis the best thing in the World for men to mind their business, when a man has business to do, let him do it, and when 'tis done, 'tis done: I know two stout Champions that had been drinking ten nights and ten days together, and at the end of the ten days and nights, one of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52570:17"/> the two would needs be gone, for I know not what worm which wrung him by the tail. Upon which the other finding that he could not stop him, bid him go to the Devil, telling him withal that if he had thought he had been a <hi>Vlincter,</hi> he wou'd never have kept him Company. And I think he was much in the right on't: For when a man has once undertaken a business, let him go thorow stitch with it.</p>
            <p>I'am of your Opinion, <hi>quo</hi> the <hi>Palatine</hi> to the <hi>Flamin</hi> (for by this the Glasses had pass'd round pretty often) when a man Fights let him Fight, and when he Drinks let him Drink, as a Sea Captain told my Grandfather of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Memory. I hate a man like poyson that flyes, when he should be laying about him and playing the Devil with two sticks. I wish I were but King of <hi>Astopia</hi> for fourscore or a hundred Years or such a Matter, by the Belly of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> if I would not feed my Grey-hounds with all those dastardly Cowards that fled from the Battle of <hi>Pavia,</hi> and left their King in the lurch, a murrain take 'em; why did they not rather die than desert that brave Prince in his Necessity? For is it not far more honourable to die in the Field brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fighting for his Life, than to live with the reproachful Character of a faint▪ hearted Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard? I have heard that <hi>Don Quixote</hi> was a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52570:17"/> man of so much mettle, that he would have fought with the Devil h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mself: immortal be his Honour: for, for my part I had rather be a Cuckold than a Coward at any time: for the one a man cannot help, the other he may. But Sir, quo the Duke of <hi>Longvisage,</hi> we have a Proverb in <hi>Astopia,</hi> better be a Coward than Fool Hardy. I know, reply'd the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> there are many good <hi>Astopian</hi> Proverbs but this is the worst that ever I heard. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the shelter of this Proverb, a man may make a thousand pretences for his Cowardice: away with it, <hi>Jarnigoy,</hi> away with it. I would not have a generous man have it in his thoughts, for fear it should make him Chicken-hearted in the day of Battel. I will be bound, <hi>Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eurs,</hi> to be fed in a great Trunk with Chocolate and Cheese-cakes all the days of my Life if my Grandfather by the Mother's side had ever worn the Crown of <hi>Astopia,</hi> had he thought of this Proverb. And of all men in the World he is the only Hero that I propose to imitate. For whether he combated in the Field or in the Chamber 'twas all one to him: and were I now as deep in the Book of Fame as He, I would not care if I were stabb'd to morrow. For then a man would be at the end of his toil, and only have the pleasure to look down from some star of the first Magnitude (for such
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52570:18"/> are the Celestial Palaces of great Princes) and see with delight the Trophies and Statues eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where set up in memory of his Heroick A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, from the Picture shining with Izing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glass and golden Leather, to the Marble Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies and Pyramid of Brass.</p>
            <p>The two <hi>Astopian</hi> Princes hearing these words, and judging of the abounding magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity of the Heart out of which the mouth spoke, lookt upon one another, but said not a word, only laid up his sayings in their breasts, to make their comments upon them at more lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. But there were others that sate at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that were so smitten with terror to behold the sternness of his Delivery, and the Resolution of his Mind, that their Hearts sank down to their Midriffs, and they made Private vows to themselves to provoke the anger of <hi>Jupiter</hi> himself, before they would incur the Palatines Indignation. Insomuch that many Company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers aw'd the Hectors and Bullys of <hi>Lutetia</hi> only by naming his name, as Nurses fright their Children with Rawhead and Bloody Bone.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap 8.</hi> Of the Pleasant discourse which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine and the two Princes had after Dinner.</head>
            <p>VVHen the Table was clear'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adorn'd with fresh Bottles, silver Monteiths, and Christal glasses, and that the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52570:18"/> Healths were beginning to go round, I cannot tell for my life how it began, neither does the <hi>Astopian</hi> History speak any thing of it, and therefore most surely it must have come in by Head and Shoulders; for that it did come in, and that there was such a discourse, we find in the fifteenth Volume of <hi>Historical and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Reflections,</hi> Printed at <hi>Cologne,</hi> in the year of Grand Revolutions. Neither was there so much improbability, but that there might be such a discourse, considering the Nature of the <hi>Astopian</hi> Soil, which does not only infuse Invention and Ingenuity into the Native In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, but also into all Foreigners that bring any Brains along with them into the Country.</p>
            <p>I wonder, said the Palatine, now I see all this neatness, brightness and cleanness upon the Table, that the <hi>Astopians</hi> so curious and nice in other things, should be so nasty in the Publick Streets. Moreover, I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, that several of your <hi>Astopian</hi> Ladies never Garter up their Stockins, but go with their hose about their heels like rough-footed Pigeons. For my part, I have such a natural Affection to cleanliness, be it in whatever part of the Body it will, that I always took care to keep my Backside as clean as the back of my Hand: so that I never went to mine Uncles, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52570:19"/> I always bethought my self of some Invention or other to perform that Office.</p>
            <p>The Palatine was going on, and would have gone on to the end of the Chapter, but that afterwards being interrupted to Pledge a Health that was going round, by that time he had taken off his Glass, he had quite forgot what he was saying. For to say truth, the greatest Imperfection which the <hi>Palatine</hi> had, was his want of Memory, which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that afterwards, when he came to bear the chief sway in <hi>Albion,</hi> whatever he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to day, by to morrow he always forgot to perform it. However the <hi>Astopian</hi> Princes <hi>ex pede Herculem,</hi> observ'd the quickness of his Wit, and how eager he was in the chase of Knowledge, when they found him Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing his Thoughts even in the most abject Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations of Nature.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> How the two <hi>Astopian</hi> Princes took their leaves of the Palatine, and the Palatine of them, and what follow'd thereupon.</head>
            <p>THere was never any Feast, how Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent soever, that lasted a whole Year together; for that there are other important businesses of this Life to be follow'd as well as eating and drinking. So that after the two <hi>Astopian</hi> Princes had cram'd their Bellies, fed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52570:19"/> like Farmers, and drank like Tinkers, they took their leaves of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> telling him a hundred Stories and Flimflams of their Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for his Person, and their readiness to serve his Interests, and assuring him withal that they would suddenly give him an opportunity to signalize that Courage &amp; Herculean Prowess which they saw not only budding, but full blown in his temper. They farther added, that the world was full of <hi>Monsters</hi> of Tyranny, <hi>Serpents</hi> and <hi>Dragons</hi> of Cruelty, <hi>Hydra</hi>'s of Usurpation, <hi>Minotaurs</hi> of Rebellion, <hi>Nemean Lyons</hi> of Rapine and Extortion, <hi>Diomeds</hi> that fed their Horses with Man's Flesh, and after all another Golden Fleece to be wrested <hi>vi &amp; armis</hi> out of the Possession of the Great Mogul, whither they made no question but his Arms would reach in time. So that whether he took upon him the Person of <hi>Theseus, Hercules, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithous, Jason,</hi> or any other of the Ancient Hero's, he would find Adventures anow to exercise his magnanimous Resolutions upon, and spread his Fame beyond whatever was yet recorded in Story.</p>
            <p>The Palatine on the other side return'd them a Cartload of thanks for their good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Protesting withal, that he would omit no occasion of shewing his readiness to be serviceable not only to themselves, but to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52570:20"/> whole Kingdom of <hi>Astopia.</hi> I confess, said he, at present you see me as it were shut up in a Cage like a Fool, but by the strength of this Arm and the favour of Heaven in a short time I hope to be in such a Condition as to expand that Royal Munificence and Gratitude which now lyes dormant and contracted within my Breast. I know that no Man but a Soveraign can be truly Liberal, and that Gratitude as the famous <hi>D. Quixot</hi> said, is but a dead Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, like Faith without Works. And therefore it is that I could wish that Fortune would offer me some favourable Opportunity to advance myself to the degree of my Ancestors of glorious Memory; I would give her for bayle the word of a Prince, that she should have no cause to repent it. You need not fear Fortune's Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; 'tis her own Interest, reply'd the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, winking with one eye, and smiling upon the half Turn, and so departed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> How the <hi>Astopians</hi> robb'd the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> Bakers of their Buns; and of the Cruel Wars that ensu'd between the two Kings of <hi>Astopia</hi> and <hi>Arragonian Belgium.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was toward the latter end of Autumn that the <hi>Astopian</hi> Vintagers lay Night and Day in the Field to keep the Crows and other Birds from eating the Grapes. Now it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52570:20"/> that several Bakers belonging to the Provinces of <hi>Arragonian Belgium,</hi> passing early upon the Road with several Loads of new Bunns, piping hot from the Oven, toward the next great City, being thereunto urg'd by the loud crys of their Stomachs, very civilly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd the <hi>Arragonian</hi> Bakers to sell them a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of their Bunns for their Money at the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket price. But the <hi>Arragonian</hi> Bakers not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refus'd the <hi>Astopian</hi> Vintagers their request, but also gave them ill Language, calling them Tooth-Gapers, Sherks, Shittabeds, Slubberde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gullions, Liquorish Whelps, Loggerheads, Lubbers, Smelfeasts, Milksops, Meacocks, Hoydons, Scoundrels, Lazy Rogues, and I know not what my self; Language indeed not to be endur'd by any Men that had any mettle in 'em. Thereupon a notable brisk <hi>Astopian,</hi> who went by the name of <hi>Sturdy Will,</hi> bearing up to the Bakers, How long, quo he, have your Horns been grown that you are become so malapert? We ask'd you civilly, and for you to refuse like Churls as you have, is no good Neighbourhood; nor do we use you so when you come to us to buy our good Wheat to make your Bunns. To which one <hi>Rounci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val,</hi> a great Cudgel Player among the Bakers, instead of returning an Answer, gave him such a lick with his Whip over the Shins, that he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52570:21"/> made the Blood spin out of his Stockins. Which the Vintagers seeing, they call'd the Husbandmen that were peeling of Walnuts hard by, to their assistance, and fell upon the Bakers with so much fury, that they made a horrid rout among 'em, and took from 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove fourscore and five dozen of Bunns. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Bakers went home, and shewing their broken Panniers, crackt Crowns and torn Jerkins to the Duke of <hi>Sowreface,</hi> the Chief Governour of all the <hi>Arragonian</hi> Provinces, demanded Satisfaction. Which being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd by the Vintagers of <hi>Astopia,</hi> a bloody War began between the two Kings of <hi>Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> and <hi>Arragonia,</hi> which will never be ended till the end of the World.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> How the Marshal of <hi>Tonneure</hi> was made Chief Commander of the <hi>Astopian</hi> Army, who chose the Palatine of <hi>Eboracum</hi> to be General of his Horse.</head>
            <p>THe King of <hi>Astopia</hi> was then a <hi>Minor,</hi> under the Tuition of the <hi>Cardinal</hi> or <hi>Arch Flamin Panourgos;</hi> who being of a testy, furious, ireful, fuming temper, presently took Pepper in the Nose, and gave Commmand to the Marshal <hi>de Tonneure,</hi> an old Souldier, and an experienced Captain, to raise the Ban and Arriere Ban, that is to say, the whole Power
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52570:21"/> of <hi>Astopia,</hi> and to fall into the <hi>Arragonian</hi> Provinces of <hi>Belgium,</hi> and there to spoil, burn, ravage and ransack all before him, and not to return back till he and his Men had devour'd either bak'd, roasted, boyl'd, or how they would themselves, All the Men, Women and Children in the Country. Immediately the Marshal <hi>de Tonneure</hi> rais'd a great Army of Horse and Foot, which he divided into Battel, Vanguard and Rearguard. In the Battel he Commanded in Person: the Vanguard he gave to the Duke of <hi>Plundermosta.</hi> The Rearguard he committed to the care of the famous Sieur <hi>Ferno-manes,</hi> an Old Officer whose Head had been twice cut off in Battel, and twice sow'd on again by the great Necromancer and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon <hi>Aqua Pendente.</hi> And the Duk of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clevere</hi> he made General of his Artillery; as being the best Engineer and Marksman in the World; for he would hit a Curran in a Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turd forty times together and never miss, at three Miles distance in a misty morning.</p>
            <p>But all this while the Marshal was to seek for a fit Person to Command his Horse. He scratch'd his Head, eat his Nails, twitch'd his Beard, bit his Lips, but nothing would do: he could not for the blood and guts of him think of a Person fit to his Mind. Well, quo he, this is a Matter of great Importance, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52570:22"/> therefore I'le consult with my Pillow about it. At his usual time to Bed he went, and there he lay rowling and trowling and revolving in his Mind what he should do. In the middle of the Night he strook a Light, took Pen, Ink, and Paper, and wrote down a List of all the Great Men in <hi>Astopia</hi> that he could think of to be fit for the Imployment; and when he had done, he put his Finger in the Inkhorn, and blotted 'em all out agen. In the midst of this Perplexity, having put his Candle out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, he compos'd himself to rest, and so fell into a slumber. And then it was (for great Men undertaking great Enterprizes are many times admonish'd in Visions) then I say it was that he thought he saw a comly person mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a slately Prancer, all in compleat Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and a Launce in his hand, with a fair Lady behind him, ride up to his Bed side. To whom the Marshal having paid his r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>spect, the Apparition made a short Speech, telling him, that he was St. <hi>Martin,</hi> the Warlike Saint, and that the Lady behind him, was the fam'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian St. <hi>Mary,</hi> who had been a Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant too in her time: that they had both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from Heaven the perplexity he was in for a General of his Horse, and therefore to put him out of his trouble, they were come to recommend to him the only person under
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52570:22"/> Heaven fit for his Design, which was the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine of <hi>Eboracum,</hi> for whose sake they would assist the <hi>Astopians</hi> with Victory, so long as the Palatine continu'd in their Service. At which the Marshal waking, <hi>Morbleu,</hi> quo he, that I should be such a Noddy to need a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from Heaven for these Directions! when I my self have had the very Person they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend so often in my thoughts. With that he got up, and wrought so effectually to the <hi>Arch Flamin</hi> at <hi>Lutetia,</hi> that the Palatine o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Eboracum</hi> was immediately sent for, and after many Complements, acquainted with the Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the Queen Regent to make him Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the <hi>Astopian</hi> Horse, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Marshal <hi>de Tonneure,</hi> desiring him withal, to put himself into an Equipage, and to hasten with all the speed he could, to his Employment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Of the Great Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parations which the Palatine made, and of the Discourse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and an Armourer about the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of his Arms.</head>
            <p>THe Palatine having this great Honour thus conferr'd upon him, lik'd the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment well enough, considering his condition▪ but when he began to revolve in his Mind the Terrours and Dangers of War, he began with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52570:23"/> the renowned <hi>Don Quixot</hi> to exclaim against that Stygian Invention of Gun-powder, that would conveigh a leaden Bullet of the most despicable Rakeshame in Nature, into the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the greatest Prince in the World; and so his <hi>Majesty,</hi> or his <hi>Highness,</hi> or his <hi>Grace</hi> must be Kill'd, and never know who hurt him. Quo the <hi>Palatine</hi> to himself, certainly Men were never created on purpose to be knockt o'the head, neither was it the intention of Nature that Men should fight and quarrel and kill one another. For I hear of no such Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment in Paradice, as, Destroy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but, Multiply and increase is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand there, and that I should like well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. 'Tis true, the Ambition of Princes is such, as that many times it sets all the world together by the Ears; but as Princes are exalted above other Men at other times, so methinks in Battels, and Bustles, and Skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes they should be exalted upon Steeples or <hi>Stands</hi> made on purpose with Prospective Glasses; where they might see the Mischief they had caus'd, but be out of danger them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. For many times the loss of the Prince is the loss of the Battel; and what does it signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for a King to be Victorious in three Battels, and be knockt o' the head in the fourth? The Proverb tells us, <hi>'Tis good sleeping in a whole
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52570:23"/> Skin:</hi> 'twas an excellent Proverb, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s own making: for I observe, that he was one that never drew a Sword, but slept in a whole Skin as long as he liv'd: and I have heard that my Grandfather, who was call'd <hi>Solomon</hi> the Second, was of his mind. For a Prince to go <hi>Stump, Stump</hi> with a woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Leg, is no way Majestical; for a Prince to have his lower or his upper Lip par'd from his Chin, and to be always shewing his Teeth, is a most unseemly thing, tho' they were all Oriental Pearl or Poetical Ivory. But then for a Prince to have both his Legs, and the one half of his Thighs lopt, saw'd, hack'd, hew'd, torn and rash'd off, and so the third part of a mans length laid up in Lavender be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he has half done with them, I must needs confess, I do not very well approve of it.</p>
            <p>These Considerations made him shrug up his Shoulders, and he could have found in his heart to have sent his <hi>Pardonnez moy</hi> to the Arch <hi>Flamin,</hi> under pretence that he had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter consider'd it. Not that there was any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the World that could scare him, only he was afraid lest a little Powder and Lead should put a stop to his courage, and prevent him from letting the World see the Strength of his Arms, and Resolution of his Mind. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was thinking one while absolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52570:24"/> decline the <hi>Moloch</hi>-like Service to which he was invited, as having no mind to be a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr to <hi>Bellona</hi> in his young years, before he had tasted the softer pleasures of the World, <hi>Bellona</hi> being no Saint in his Calendar; and believing his Mother had Interest enough to procure him a Scarlet Hat; which would be a more easie way of living; besides, that if he found his Courage meliorate hereafter, his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing initiated into the Ceremonies of the Pagans would be no hind'rance to him from being a great General when he had a mind to it. But this he thought would be a degrading his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and totally annihilate the High Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which the World had already conceiv'd of his valour. Another while he was for absent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself in a female Dress, and Spinning or Carding among the <hi>Lutetian</hi> Ladies; and if the worst should come to the worst, or that some cunning <hi>Ulysses</hi> should find him out, it would be no more than what <hi>Achilles</hi> the stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>Hero</hi> in the World had done before him; and so be look'd upon as a Frolick, or else as a Prognostick that he would become a second <hi>Achilles,</hi> whose Actions he had propos'd to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in all things.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:52570:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ch. 13.</hi> Of his Discourse with his Page about being invulnerable.</head>
            <p>IN this <hi>Quandary,</hi> the Palatine call'd to him his Trusty Page <hi>Epistemon. Epistemon,</hi> quo he, what dost thou think of this smothering, smoaky, brimstony Hell upon Earth, as the World has now made it, War, whither I am now press'd to go? Oh Sir, reply'd <hi>Epistemon,</hi> 'tis the only way to try whether you are of Mortal race, or no. The ancient Stories tell ye, how that <hi>Thetys</hi> cover'd all her Children over head and ears in the fire to that purpose. 'Twas to very fine purpose indeed, quo the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, for by that curiosity of hers, she burnt all her Children to Ashes, like a She-devil as she was. However, quo <hi>Epistemon,</hi> her Son <hi>Achilles</hi> was sav'd by being anointed all over with <hi>Ambrosia:</hi> 'tis true indeed they forgot to anoint one of his Lips, but which I can't tell, and that was a little sing'd, and prov'd a mortal Disfigurement to him as long as he liv'd. Ay but, quo the Palatine, where is that <hi>Ambrosia</hi> to be had? I would not forget to noint both my Lips, as well as the rest of my Body, I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thee, Boy. <hi>Morbleu,</hi> quo <hi>Epistemon,</hi> I can't tell where that <hi>Ambrosia</hi> is to be got, but I can tell ye where something like it is to be had. What think you, Sir, of that same Oyl which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52570:25"/> the <hi>Astopians</hi> affirm to have been sent down from Heaven, and have kept it for these eight hundred years in a large glass Viol in the City of <hi>Durocortum?</hi> Surely, Sir, it must be either <hi>Ambrosia,</hi> or something like <hi>Ambrosia,</hi> or else the <hi>Astopians</hi> would never have preserv'd it so long and so charily. You mean the Oyl with which the <hi>Astopian</hi> Kings are anointed at their Coronations. The very same Sir, quo <hi>Episte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> Puh, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> that can't be the <hi>Ambrosia</hi> that <hi>Achilles</hi> was nointed with: for we find the <hi>Astopian</hi> Kings were vulnerable. <hi>Hen.</hi> the 3d. was stabb'd. and <hi>Hen.</hi> the 4th. my Grandfather was stabb'd. O Sir, quo <hi>Episte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that was because they were not nointed all over: had the Daggers lit upon those places where those Kings had been nointed, my Life for yours, the Ragamuffins might as well have enter'd a piece of Steel. This is sure, there is nothing but <hi>Nectar</hi> or <hi>Ambrosia</hi> in Heaven; and it can't be <hi>Nectar,</hi> for it is too greasie to drink, and therefore it must be <hi>Ambrosia.</hi> Or if this Project does not please ye, Sir, said <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemon,</hi> what think ye of going down to <hi>Hell,</hi> as <hi>Aeneas</hi> from whom you are descended in a direct Line, did, and plunging your self over head and ears in the Waters of <hi>Styx,</hi> as <hi>Thetys</hi> did <hi>Achilles,</hi> all but his Leg, and that prov'd his bane; but what a man does himself, he's
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52570:25"/> sure of doing to the purpose. But then the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine was afraid lest <hi>Cerberus</hi> should bite him by the Shins, and if the Sore should Gangreen, that he should never be able to get back again. Under these Anxieties of Mind,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Now com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s his Conference with <hi>Vulcan</hi> the Armourer.</head>
            <p>FRiend, <hi>Epistemon,</hi> quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> I have heard, that if a man comes into the world in his Mothers Smicket, he shall be the most fortunate man in the world. I cannot tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I were so or no. But I should be loth to trust to that. For I can tell by experience that Womens Linnen is seldom proof against sligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Batteries than those of a Cannon Bullet. And therefore fetch me hither <hi>Vulcan</hi> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour maker; they say he is a famous Fellow, and rare in his Art. For I would fain fight as safely as I can; that's but common Prudence; and Nature teaches every man to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. <hi>Epistemon</hi> flew, and <hi>Vulcan</hi> came in a Trice: To whom the <hi>Palatine,</hi> Is your Name <hi>Vulcan,</hi> Friend? My name Sir, is <hi>Vulcan,</hi> and I make Suits of Arms for Gentlemen that want them; that is to say, I am an <hi>Armour-Taylor</hi> by Trade. Where do you live? quo the Palatine. Here in <hi>Lutetia,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Armour-Taylor.</hi> Then you are not that <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:52570:26"/> I mean, quo the Palatine: I mean that <hi>Vulcan</hi> that kept Shop at <hi>Aetna</hi> in <hi>Sicilie,</hi> whose Journeymen were call'd <hi>Cyclops</hi>'s, they that made <hi>Pluto</hi> a Helmet, and gave it him for nothing; the vertue of which was so rare, that where e're he put it on, he became invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible; Can you make me such a one? I will not undertake it, Sir; for that Trade, like Painting in Glass, is quite lost now: that <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> of whom you spoke last, never left his Receipt behind him. What can you do then? Can you make me such a Sute of Armour as your <hi>Namesake</hi> made <hi>Achilles,</hi> that no human force could penetrate, full Cannon proof? 'Slife Sir, how can I do that, when a Cannon Bullet will make its way through the sides of a First Rate Ship three foot thick, all massie Oak? Then you can do nothing: Alas Sir, these Cannon Bullets have quite spoil'd our Trade: for what signifies it for men to buy Suits of Armour, when they signifie nothing? Formerly when men shot nothing but Darts and Arrows, or sharp Stakes harden'd at one end in the Fire, we could make a shift to deal with 'em well enough. I wish the Devil were to eat all the Cannon Bullets that ever were or ever will be, red hot for his Supper this very Night, and then our Trade would mend. Is there no way then to fend off these Cannon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52570:26"/> Bullets? quo the <hi>Palatine:</hi> they make my heart shiver every time I think of 'em. No way but one, quo <hi>Vulcan;</hi> a good thick long Bush of Hair for the Head, <hi>Sampson</hi>'s Strength lay in in his Hair; nay, the whole Strength of the City <hi>Megarae</hi> lay in King <hi>Nysus</hi>'s purple Lock, and what's a Cannon Bullet to the whole Strength of a City? And we find that <hi>Gara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantua,</hi> after a great Battel, comb'd out no less than fifty Cannon Bullets out of his Hair; which he could never have done, had not the thickness of his Bush natural dampt 'em, and kept 'em from going farther. But what shall we do for the rest of the Body? quo the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine. That must be done, quo the Armou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, by means of a Round Wall, about four foot thick, made of a certain Parget mix'd and temper'd with Eggs, like the Walls of <hi>Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntria</hi> in <hi>Albion,</hi> which may be so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd, as to be girt on like a Campaign Coat. Who the Devil shall be able to carry it, quo the <hi>Palatine?</hi> Why Sir, quo the <hi>Armourer,</hi> there are s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veral both here in <hi>Lut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia,</hi> and in other places, that can wear a Stone Doublet for a Twelvemonth or two years together, and make nothing of it. You must exercise, an't please your Highness, as <hi>Milo</hi> did by his Calf, first carry a little Wall, then a small Wall, then a bigger Wall, till you come to be able
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52570:27"/> to carry the Wall of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rfection. Hang all your Walls, quo the Page, my Master shall carry no Walls: I have lit upon the true way at length. Sir, said he, you have three Pagan Deities at Command, St. <hi>Loyola,</hi> St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> and St. <hi>Francis,</hi> there's not a straw to choose. Ply any one of these, and they will as surely send you a Life Guard of four Arch Angels, as ever St. <hi>Francis</hi> pass'd the <hi>Danaw</hi> in his Cowle. These Arch Angels will guard ye, one before, another behind, and one of each side, and when they see a Cannon Bullet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward ye from any corner of the Wind, will catch it like a Stool Ball, and throw it to the Devil. Courage, Master, <hi>allons,</hi> in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Sanctae Mariae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Palatine</hi> lik'd this Project very well: However for more surety, he was resolv'd that <hi>Vulcan</hi> should make him a Sute of Armour to boot. Which the Armourer promised to do, of Enchanted Tiffany steep'd in the Blood of the <hi>Minotaur</hi> which <hi>Theseus</hi> kill'd; of which the Armourer said, he had above a Gallon left.</p>
            <p>This tickl'd the Palatine more than any thing had been yet said; so that he bid the Armourer go on and prosper.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:52570:27"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> How a certain Doctor came to the Palatine and prescrib'd him a Diet to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease his Courage.</head>
            <p>HOw the Devil the <hi>Palatine</hi> came to know it, there is no author that makes menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but it seems it did come to his knowledge, how that <hi>Hercules</hi> receiv'd the greatest part of his Education from a Physitian. This brought to his mind, that Herbs and Flowers had many hidden Qualities and Operations upon the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Humours of Men: Some encreas'd the blood, and some encreas'd choler; and how that <hi>Circe</hi> and <hi>Medea</hi> made use of Herbs and Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Moss of dead Mens Skulls, the Brains of Bats, and Livers of Porcupines, and such like Ingredients in all their charms and enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: how the one boil'd her Father to a young man, and the other turn'd men into Swine: Upon these considerations, the <hi>Palatine</hi> sending for several Physicians, ask'd them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the nature of man might not be alter'd by Diet: and whether there were not some sorts of Diet more proper for a Souldier than others. This was a Question he might have put to half the Colledge of <hi>Physicians,</hi> and have been as wise as he was before, had it not been for one man that knew more than all the Rest. Who hearing the Question propounded stay'd till all the rest of the Doctors were gone; and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52570:28"/> then addressing himself to the <hi>Palatine,</hi> Sir, said He, I have heard your Question, and understand what you mean. And therefore do but observe my directions, and if you be not one of the most valiant men in the World, never trust me more. To which the <hi>Palatine</hi> consenting, the Physician order'd him for his first course to feed upon nothing but the plucks or Entrails of Lyons, and the Marrow of Wolves, Bears and Tygres: and for his second course to eat nothing but game Cocks, and the Brains of Quails and Magpies, (being a Bird particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consecrated to <hi>Mars</hi>) for a Month or six weeks together, &amp; then to make him a Coat of a Tan'd Elephants Skin, lin'd through with the bags of ten Ostridges Stomacks, and overlaid with the scales of a spit fire Dragon. For that the Ostridges Stomacks being of a steely sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance concocted by the natural heat of those birds, acquir'd a thickness no less impenetrable, than the Dragons scales continually harden'd in the Sun. <hi>Probatum est,</hi> Sir, quo the Doctor. Do but use this method once a year, and you may defie <hi>Jupiter</hi> with all his Thunder bolts. By my Troth, Dr. quo the Palatine, I wish you had come a little sooner, and you might have spar'd me the expence of a suit of Armour, which I have newly bespoke. But 'tis no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a man can't be too cautious of himself.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52570:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> Of the wonderful Atchievements which the Palatine performed in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of General of the Horse.</head>
            <p>VVIthal these preliminary Cautions the <hi>Palatine</hi> thus Fed, thus Dieted and Arm'd from Head to Foot, repair'd to the <hi>Astopian</hi> Army; where he was highly caress'd by the Marshal <hi>de Tonneure,</hi> and presently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested in the Command of <hi>Lieutenant General</hi> of the <hi>Astopian</hi> Army, and General of the Horse. But Heavens! to repeat the wonderful Atchievements which the <hi>Palatine</hi> perform'd, would fill a Cartload of Paper. <hi>Francisco Viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dico,</hi> the Historian of those times averrs them to have so far transcended humane Imagination, that he is very shy of relating them, for fear of being accompted <hi>Homo Mendax;</hi> a Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter which he abominated above all things in the World. He says that in one battel the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine mow'd down with his own hands three whole Regiments at once: but withal he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges that the <hi>Palatine</hi> had this ill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune attending him at the same time, that the Men were no sooner kill'd but they started up alive again, and put him to new trouble; so that after he had sweat, and toild, and moil'd, and laid about him like another <hi>Sampson,</hi> the Victory was never the nearer. Which the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52570:29"/> Marshal <hi>de Tonneure</hi> beholding, these are brave Acts indeed, quo he, but at this rate we shall never carry away the <hi>Golden Fleece.</hi> 'Slife, quo the <hi>Palatine</hi> to the <hi>Marshal,</hi> what would you have me to do, Sir? I kill'd 'em thrice, and they would not die. I agree with ye, Noble Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine quo the Marshal; therefore let's retreat for the present, and kill 'em again when they are in a better humour.</p>
            <p>Another time, says the same <hi>Historian,</hi> the Marshal was to march with his Army by a great Castle that stood in the middle of a wide Lake: but finding he could not pass by, without being cruelly gall'd by the great Guns from the Fort, he signifi'd his desire to have it taken in. Which when none of his Great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders beside would undertake, the <hi>Palatine</hi> readily undertook. To which purpose, he chose out a Regiment of Dragoons, and shoeing all the Horses with Cork, he rode full speed up to the Castle Walls. But when he came there, he call'd to mind that the Souldiers had left their Skaling Ladders behind them: and so he was fain to gallop back again, not without some loss. This was a brave attempt you'l say; and if the Palatine fail'd in the enterprise, it was not for want of Valour, but for want of Skaling Ladders.</p>
            <p>But the Marshal <hi>de Tonneure</hi> attributed all
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52570:29"/> these Miscarriages to Fortune, who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways an Enemy to Vertue. However he gave the <hi>Palatine</hi> high Encomiums. Insomuch that falling dangerously sick toward the latter end of the Campaign, and believing he should die, he sent word to the <hi>Flamin Panourgus,</hi> that if he intended that the Affairs of <hi>Astopia</hi> should prosper, he should make choice of the Noble, Valorous and Fortunate <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Eboracum</hi> to succeed him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> How the Palatine was Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented out of <hi>Astopia,</hi> and of something else beside.</head>
            <p>BUt notwithstanding all these great At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements and vast Pieces of Service, perform'd by the Palatine; and many more that lie conceal'd from the Knowledge of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to this very day, for want of an Impartial Historian; notwithstanding the signal Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials of the Grand Marshal <hi>de Tonneure,</hi> the <hi>Astopians</hi> took no more notice of what he had done, than if he had done nothing at all. Some say, that Fame had taken a Mortal peek against the <hi>Palatine,</hi> and lay at Fortune night and day to stop the Progress of his growing renown. She alleadg'd that all the last Summer, she had been so hurri'd from Post to Pillar to spread the Glory of his Heroick Actions, that she was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52570:30"/> quite tir'd off her Legs; and that the Pinions of her wings were so sore, that she was hardly able to wagg 'em: So that if any other great Captain should have occasion for her, she knew not how to order her sprats. And therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought Fame to put a stop to the Career of the Palatines Valour for a time till she had strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd her wings with a Plaister of <hi>Oxycroceum</hi> and <hi>Paracelsus</hi> which she had laid on for that purpose. Now in regard that <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> piss both in a quill, <hi>Fortune,</hi> to do her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <hi>Fame</hi> a kindness, goes to the <hi>Flamin Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourgus,</hi> and to lessen the <hi>Palatines</hi> Reputation, tells him there was no such thing as the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines mowing down three Regiments at a time. and that the Adventure of the <hi>Castle</hi> in the <hi>Lake</hi> was a meer story. 'Tis a question whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Panourgus</hi> would have believ'd it, or no, (for the News went for currant Coyn, and was printed and confirm'd by all the <hi>Lutetian</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ets) had it not been for an Exigent of <hi>State</hi> which Fortune impos'd upon the <hi>Flamin.</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Astopians</hi> finding that the <hi>Arragonian Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians</hi> were too hard for 'em, sent away their Embassadors to <hi>Oliverero Soldan</hi> of <hi>Albion,</hi> with four hundred Camels loaden with money to purchase his friendship and Assistance. The <hi>Soldan</hi> took their Money, but told the <hi>Flamin</hi> withal that unless he sent away the Palatine,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52570:30"/> and all that adher'd to him out of <hi>Astopia,</hi> he would keep the Money, and do nothing for it! Heavens Sir! quo the Ambassadours, as if such a trifle as that could break any squares between <hi>Panourgus</hi> and the Soldan of <hi>Albion.</hi> What is the <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Eboracum</hi> to us? If he have done any thing for Us, which is more than we know, the <hi>Elamin</hi> does not intend to run a way in his Debt. <hi>Bougre Diable,</hi> let him go; we hope we have in <hi>Astopia</hi> five hundred as good as He. The Business being thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, <hi>Panourgus</hi> who had his Brains well boyl'd, had a Flea presently ready to put in his Ear, and sent him without delay a Nosegay of Complements, to let him understand the reason of the Message: the Cogency of Affairs that constrain'd him to it; and the unexpres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible sorrow of all the <hi>Astopian</hi> Court; but that the Condition of the Kingdom was such, that it was not in their Power to help it; with many other <hi>Goodly Good morrows</hi> of the same nature. Of all which proceedings the <hi>Palatine</hi> had perfect Intelligence, and was so little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to see himself so rejected and despis'd, that instead of taking it for an Affront, and seeking his Revenge, he afterwards lov'd, the <hi>Astopian</hi> King so much the better for it, that he could never be drawn from Espousing his Interest. Nothing vex'd him so much, as that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52570:31"/> he must be forc'd to leave unaccomplish'd a Love-Intreague with an <hi>Astopian</hi> Lady, to which he had been invited by a <hi>Lutetian</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curess; for <hi>Lutetia</hi> was a City where you might as well take the Moon by the Teeth, as separate <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> Of one of the strangest things that ever happen'd.</head>
            <p>IT is a common thing, as all men know, for Ladies to fall in love with great Hero's, tho' they never saw them in their Lives; the great and famous Atchievements of the Valiant Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine having the same operation upon their Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as their Majestick Behaviours and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lineaments had upon his Eyes: For <hi>Cupid</hi>'s Darts do not always enter in at the Eyes, but sometimes pierce through the Ears, as being the shorter cut to the heart. Who this Lady was, whether <hi>Dutchess,</hi> or <hi>Marchioness,</hi> or <hi>Viscoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess,</hi> or plain <hi>my Lady,</hi> without Welt or Guard, the Historian does not make mention. But by the sequel, it appear'd that she had neither seen nor spoken with the Palatine in her life; only she was in love with him up to the Ears for the sake of his spreading glory: and heavily tormented to hear that he was so suddenly to leave <hi>Astopia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One day as the Palatine was sitting alone,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52570:31"/> and reflecting among other things upon the Ingratitude of the <hi>Astopians,</hi> a Letter was brought him with this Superscription:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>To the most Passionately beloved by all fair Ladies, had he had wit to understand it.</hi> T. T. J. S. S. E. A. A.</q>
            <p>When the <hi>Palatine</hi> read this Superscription, never was Bell-Founder in such an amaze when his Metal miscarries. He ponder'd, consider'd, and studied, but could not imagine from whence it should come: He ask'd the Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger who sent it; but he knew nothing of the matter. But when he open'd the Letter, then he was in a double confusion; for there was no more Writing to be seen within side than upon the back of his hand, only a Table Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, enchas'd in a plain Gold Ring. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue goy,</hi> quo the Palatine to himself, a visible Ring from an invisible Lady! Then making another pause; but hold—said he, what if it should be a present from <hi>Gyges?</hi> With that he put on the Ring, and went to the Looking-Glass, but finding that he could see himself, he call'd for his Secretary. <hi>Polysthenes,</hi> said he, here's a Ring sent me in a Paper seal'd up without any Writing: and with that he shew'd him the Ring and the blank Letter. Sir, quo <hi>Polysthenes,</hi> this Ring could never come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Words; but there are many ways to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52570:32"/> write upon Paper, yet so as the Writing shall never be seen. Thereupon he held the Paper to the fire, to see if it were writ with <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniac</hi> mix'd and dissolv'd in water. Then he dipt it in fair water, to find whether it were writ with Juice of <hi>Tithymall.</hi> Then he held it to the Candle, to see whether it were done with the Juice of white Onyons. After that, he rubb'd it over with Oyl of Walnuts, to find whether it were writ with a <hi>Lixivium</hi> of Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree Ashes. Then he wash'd it over with the Milk of a Woman at that time suckling her first Child, to know whether it were writ with red Toads blood. Then he rubb'd it with the ashes of a Swallows Nest, to find whether it was written with the dew that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alls upon your winter Cherries. But when he had try'd these and several other ways, and found that it was nothing but a meer dumb piece of Paper, Sir, said he, by the vertue of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> I know not what to say to't. I have employ'd all my Art, and can find nothing. With that looking very narrowly upon the Ring it self, they found Engrav'd within side, <hi>I Bleed.</hi> Now the Devil take the <hi>Flamin</hi> and the Soldan of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion</hi> both together, quo the Palatine. Here's a Lady lyes a bleeding for me; and I know I have a Balsam would cure her: what shall I do in this case? who it is, I know not; go I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52570:32"/> cannot; stay I must not. Thus agitated and perplex'd in mind, he laid himself down upon his Couch, and fell asleep.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 19.</hi> How the <hi>Palatine</hi> was entertain'd by the Governour of <hi>Belgic Arragonia;</hi> and how he vow'd to be reveng'd upon the <hi>Astopians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe <hi>Palatine</hi> being thus sent packing out of <hi>Astopia</hi> retir'd to the <hi>Satrape</hi> of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Arragonia,</hi> who receiv'd him as the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian</hi> King <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> did <hi>Themistocles,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him the Revenue of several Provinces for the maintenance of him and his Retinue: one Province to find him Butcher's Meat, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fowl of all sorts; a third to furnish him with Wine, and a fourth to supply him with white Bread and Grand Salads. One time as the Palatine and the <hi>Satrape</hi> were discoursing together, the <hi>Palatine</hi> fell into a most horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rage against the <hi>Astopians;</hi> you would have sworn it had been the <hi>Conquerour</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> in his Cups. He gave 'em all the reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Names that his fury could invent; and vow'd never to wash his hands but in <hi>Astopian</hi> Blood; and every Morning to have the Hars<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of an <hi>Astopian</hi> roasted and stufft with Sage for his Breakfast. Which being related to the <hi>Astopians,</hi> they trembl'd for fear like the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52570:33"/> of a Cathedral. And the same threats and Menaces of the Palatine being carry'd to the Marshal <hi>de Tonneure,</hi> notwithstanding all his former Encomiums, Oh!—quo he, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine's a young Prince; give him leave to huff and ding for his living; words break no Bones: when all's done, 'tis the Coach-wheel, not the Fly that raises the Dust.</p>
            <p>On the other side, the <hi>Palatine,</hi> to shew that he meant as he said, set great Traps upon the Borders of <hi>Astopia,</hi> which he baited with <hi>alamode Gallimawfries;</hi> by which means he caught several of the <hi>Astopians,</hi> and then caus'd 'em to be minc'd as small as Herbs to the Pot, made Marrow Puddings of the inside of their Bones, and Pyes of the Meat mix'd with Currants and Raisins after the manner of <hi>Albion.</hi> Which the <hi>Astopians</hi> observing, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately laid great heaps of Gunpowder under the Traps, and when the <hi>Belgians</hi> came early in the Morning to see for their Prey, set fire to their Trains and blew up Traps, Trap-setters and all. Which so incens'd the <hi>Palatine,</hi> and caus'd such an overflowing of his Choler, that he fell into such a violent Loosness through the sharpness of the humour, that his <hi>Duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> was become almost as slender as a Base Lutestring; and he had certainly paid dear for his Traps, had not a notable Artist
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52570:33"/> stopp'd the Orifice of his Intestines with the end of a huge Elephants Tooth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 20.</hi> Of the Great War between the <hi>Astopians</hi> and the <hi>Belgic-Arragonians;</hi> where you may probably hear of something which the Palatine did to his Eternal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</head>
            <p>THe War was now grown very hot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Belgic-Arragonians,</hi> and the <hi>Astopians,</hi> to whose aid the <hi>Soldan</hi> of <hi>Albion</hi> had sent a very great Host, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Caledonian Knight.</hi> To be short, the <hi>Astopians</hi> swore they would have the Strong City of <hi>Dunquerka</hi> from the <hi>Arrago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians;</hi> and the <hi>Arragonians</hi> swore they should not. To this purpose, the <hi>Astopians</hi> belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guer'd the Place, and the <hi>Arragonians</hi> hasten'd to relieve it, and the Palatine had a Battalion of Horse. And now the two Armies were got very near together. For the <hi>Astopians</hi> went to meet the Enemy, and the Enemy came to meet them: and indeed the <hi>Arragonians</hi> had such a Confidence in the Valour and Conduct of the Palatine, that they car'd not a fig for the <hi>Astopians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the <hi>Arragonians</hi> lay within less than two Mile of the Enemies, it happen'd that the Boys in the next Village to the <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonian</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52570:34"/> Camp, had made them a great Paper Kite, and in the dark of the Night had mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it aloft in the Air with a Lanthorn and Candle fastn'd to it. When the Palatine spy'd it, by St. <hi>Martha</hi>'s Petticoat, quo he, St. <hi>George</hi> for <hi>England</hi> with a Lanthorn and Candle in his hand.—the Heavens smile upon us, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory's ours, as sure as a Louse in a Taylor's Bosom. Hold—quo the Palatine, I rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be some Soul let out of Purgatory, and going directly to Paradice; only stops by the way to piss down Benedictions upon the Army. But let it be what it will, my heart's a pound lighter to see it.</p>
            <p>The next Morning the ordering the Army was committed wholly to the Palatine's care: for they say the <hi>Arragonians</hi> were so bewitch'd as to think him the most experienc'd Captain in the World: and all agree, that had it not been for certain <hi>If's</hi> and <hi>Buts</hi> that oppos'd his good Fortune, he had certainly won the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory: For just as he was going to Charge the Enemy, his Horse cast a Shoe, so that he was forc'd to Wheel off to the next Farrier to get his Prancer new shod, and his Battalion was forc'd to follow for the Guard of his Person, and so there was one opportunity lost. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, no sooner had he got his Horse shod, but away he came powdering back, Lightning
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52570:34"/> in his Eyes, Thunder in his Hand▪ and had certainly cut in pieces two whole Squadrons of the <hi>Albionian</hi> Infantry, had not a Fellow more daring than all the rest, stept out of his Rank, and given him such a terrible flap with a Fox tail that he beat him off his Horse. The <hi>Arragonians</hi> seeing their Leader fall, presently recoyl'd, and the <hi>Albionians</hi> pressing on, took the <hi>Palatine</hi> Captive. But then it was, that St. <hi>Dominic</hi> stood his Friend; for immediately he darted himself from the <hi>Empyrean</hi> Heaven, and chang'd the Palatine into a Conger Eel, and so he slipt out of his Enemies hands. At what time perceiving the Battel to be lost, all he could do, was to put himself in the Rear, where he so bestir'd his stumps, that he stopp'd the pursuit of the Victors. Tho others say, that he was more beholding to his Policy than Strength; for seeing the Battel lost, and all his Men in a rout and flying, he order'd 'em still as they fled to keep fizling and farting for their Lives; which it was the more easie for them to do, considering the fear they were in; &amp; by that means there was such a thick stink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fog for ten Miles round, that the <hi>Astopians</hi> and <hi>Albionians,</hi> not being able to see Wood for Trees, let 'em go. Others will have it, that when he saw the Battel begin to totter, he sent for <hi>Adrians Wall</hi> from the Borders of <hi>Cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia▪</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:52570:35"/> and clapt it between the Victors and the Vanquish'd, to the great disappointment of the Pursuers. For in regard that it is by all agreed that the <hi>Palatine</hi> perform'd wonders at this Battel, they must be such wonders as these, or none at all; for the Devil a bit can we hear of any other that he did: and to say he did none, would be a contradiction to History.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 21.</hi> How the <hi>Palatine</hi> was restor'd to his <hi>Palatinate</hi> in <hi>Albion,</hi> and how he rode Tantivy to <hi>Papimania.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SOon after this, the Soldan of <hi>Albion</hi> dy'd, and the Thirty Tyrants resum'd their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Authority, and chose for their General the Knight of the <hi>Golden Tulip:</hi> but the <hi>Albionians</hi> being quite tyr'd with the Cruelties and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of the Thirty Tyrants, resolv'd to recall and restore to his Right the Son of the King of <hi>Albion,</hi> whom the <hi>Soldan</hi> had put to Death, at that time an Exile in the Dominions of the <hi>Arragonians.</hi> We shall not trouble the Reader with the Ceremonies and Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Restoration, it will be enough for our purpose to let ye know that at the same time, the Palatine was also restor'd to his Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate of <hi>Eboracum,</hi> and all the Titles and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities thereunto belonging. And now calling to mind certain Negotiations with the <hi>Mufti</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:52570:35"/> of <hi>Papimania,</hi> the Chief City of <hi>Pagan-land,</hi> he bought him a flying Horse of the same breed, and lineally descended from that upon which <hi>Perseus</hi> rode over the Sea, to deliver <hi>Andromeda,</hi> and away he gallop'd tantivy a thousand Miles an hour, till he came to the <hi>Muftie</hi>'s Palace, where he lay <hi>incognito</hi> four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score and nineteen years, and every Morning drank such large Mornings Draughts of the Brewage of the Country, and was so intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the strength of the Liquor which was the next degree to Poison, that he never was in his right Senses afterwards, but was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a <hi>Papimanie-Delirium,</hi> which brought him at length to one of the most despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Convulsions that ever were known. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from <hi>Papimanie,</hi> he call'd upon the King of <hi>Astopia,</hi> still <hi>incognito</hi> as before, with whom he made a League of perpetual Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, like those of <hi>Theseus</hi> and <hi>Pirythous,</hi> vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never to forsake one another, tho' it were to go down to the Regions of King <hi>Pluto</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There he also took a solemn Oath upon the Sacred Altar of the Pagan Deity call'd <hi>Omnium Sanctorum,</hi> like <hi>Hannibal</hi> against the <hi>Romans,</hi> to Extirpate all the Christians from the face of the Earth; and particularly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the <hi>Belgians,</hi> to annihilate the Grand Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of <hi>Albion,</hi> and to reduce the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52570:36"/> under the Tyrannical Government of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopia.</hi> This done, he return'd back into <hi>Albion,</hi> where he liv'd under-ground for some years in a Palace belonging to the Grand Duke of <hi>Hades,</hi> till the <hi>Mufti</hi> sent two Messengers for him, <hi>Sea-Fight</hi> and <hi>Slaughter,</hi> and fetch'd him out by the Head and Ears.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 22.</hi> Of the great Herring War between the <hi>Belgians</hi> and the <hi>Albionians,</hi> and how the Palatine was made <hi>Archithalassus</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THo' the <hi>Palatine</hi> liv'd under-ground, as we said before, yet he did not live idle; for thither resorted privately to him all the <hi>State Moles, Incendiaries, Boutefeu's,</hi> Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners of Government, Spies, Eevedroppers, Cajoulers of Princes, all Emissaries belonging to the <hi>Muftie</hi> of <hi>Papimania,</hi> and all or the greatest part of the Order of <hi>Loyola,</hi> one of the greatest and most Bigotted Pagans in the World.</p>
            <p>With these, the <hi>Palatine</hi> Day and Night, Weekly, Monthly, Yearly, had his private Cabals and secret Consultation in his Palace under-ground, for they durst not appear in Publick, for fear of the Laws of <hi>Albion,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch were very strict and severe against them; so that if any of them were caught they were
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52570:36"/> presently Hang'd up without Mercy. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were the Palatines only <hi>Croneys,</hi> and by their means he held a faithful and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Correspondence with the <hi>Muftie</hi> of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimania,</hi> and the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> in order to destroy the Christians. And to prevent their being discover'd, the <hi>Muftie</hi> and the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> sent the <hi>Palatine</hi> fifteen hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Tuns of <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> to lull all those Christians asleep that had any Eye upon their Actions. They had also among them an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted <hi>Mercuries Wand,</hi> made of pure Gold, with which if they did but touch the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of a Christian, he fell into a profound <hi>Caros,</hi> and never wak'd again. And thus the <hi>Muftie,</hi> the King of <hi>Astopia,</hi> and the <hi>Palatine,</hi> were a combin'd <hi>Triumvirate</hi> to grind all the Christians to Powder, as the chief Captain of the Hebrews did the Golden Calf, and to strew the dust of their powder'd Carcasses in the wind.</p>
            <p>In order to this Design, it was concluded in the first place to destroy the <hi>Belgians.</hi> For at that time the Christians of <hi>Belgium,</hi> and the Christians of <hi>Albion</hi> were in League together, &amp; the Pagan <hi>Triumvirs</hi> thought it impossible to accomplish their Ends, unless they could divide the two most Potent States in the World of all the Christian Nations. So they made Herrings the Ground of the Quarrel thus.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:52570:37"/>
            <p>It is well known to all the World, that the Pagans of <hi>Papimania</hi> are great Devourers of Herrings, and at one time of the year they feed only upon Herrings, as the Ancient Gods fed upon <hi>Ambrosia.</hi> Now in regard the King of <hi>Albion</hi> had a prodigiously vast Herring Pond in the North Seas, which no body else had, so that he could supply all those vast Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, possessed by the Pagans, with Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. Which was the reason that the King of <hi>Albion</hi>'s Herring Revenue, had it been well manag'd, was lookt upon to be of greater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue than all the Golden Mines of <hi>Peru</hi> in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> belonging to the King of the <hi>Arragoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> there being never a Herring in this Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Pond, but what, as soon as it is caught, turns immediately into Gold. So that if the <hi>Hesperian</hi> Orchard deserv'd an always waking <hi>Argos</hi> for the Guard of half a score Golden Pippin Trees, the King of <hi>Albion</hi> ought to have had a Million of <hi>Argos</hi>'s to watch this Herring-Pond.</p>
            <p>But the King of <hi>Albion</hi> not being so careful of his Herring-Pond as he should have been, the <hi>Belgians</hi> attracted by the great noise of the Gain which was made by this golden Fish, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the King of <hi>Albion</hi>'s <hi>Herring-Pond,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the King of <hi>Albion</hi> had no more right to the Herring-Pond than they, since the wide
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52570:37"/> Sea was common to all, there being no Land-Marks, Mounds, Fences nor Hedges to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish Propriety upon the Ocean: and thus in a short time the <hi>Belgians</hi> made more Profit of the King of <hi>Albion</hi>'s Herring-Pond than he did himself.</p>
            <p>'Slife, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> there's ne're a <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> in the World shall fish in our Herring-Pond; and with that he left his under-ground Palace, and remov'd to the Forrest of <hi>San Jacomo;</hi> moreover, he took up Lodgings in <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> it self, where the King kept his Court; where he lay day and night at the K. of <hi>Albion,</hi> to incense him against the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians.</hi> Sir, quo he, the <hi>Belgians</hi> rob your Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring-Pond: can you sit still and suffer such an Affront? How shall I help it? quo the King. Beat 'em, quo the Palatine. 'Tis soon said, quo the King. With that in a great Rage, quo the Palatine, say but the word, and I'le do the work with two or three Oyster-Boats. Is not all the Sea yours that surrounds your Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions? Nay, does not your chief Justiciary's Warrant reach as far as a man may ken Land, and shall your Power be confin'd? The King of <hi>Albion</hi> being thus incens'd, sent to the <hi>Belgians</hi> to forbear fishing his Herring-Pond: but the <hi>Belgians</hi> swore <hi>Sacrament,</hi> They would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear; and so the Quarrel began.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:52570:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 23.</hi> Of the Great Preparations which the Palatine made to fight the <hi>Belgians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe War being thus agreed upon, the King of <hi>Albion</hi> made the Palatine his <hi>Archithalassus;</hi> and to him committed the whole Care and Management of this Bloody Contest. And that he might not send the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> upon a First day of <hi>April</hi> Errand, he rigg'd out a Stupendious Fleet, much bigger than <hi>Agamemnon</hi>'s when he sail'd against <hi>Troy,</hi> tho' it cost <hi>Homer</hi> half the Second Book of his <hi>Iliads</hi> to give a List of the Ships and Commanders. The Fleet with which <hi>Xerxes</hi> cover'd the <hi>Asiatic</hi> Ocean was not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with it. Nay, if I should say that the Terrour of the Waves which broke the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comans</hi> at <hi>Lepanto,</hi> was but a Fleet of Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karel Boats to it, I should say nothing but the Truth.</p>
            <p>But when the <hi>Palatine</hi> went aboard, and heard the great Guns Roar and Bark like so many <hi>Cerberus</hi>'s, he call'd to see the Bullets which those massie brazen spit-fires carri'd. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had felt the weight of three or four of the biggest, in a most vehement and terrible rage, quo he, Celestial foresight was too short, to make the ribs of man so weak, knowing the time would come when these unsanctifi'd Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52570:38"/> would be in use. But considering that thô a man had but weak ribs, yet he had a strong Brain, he began to think whether a man's brains might not be cunning enough to save his ribs. He remember'd how he had secur'd his bones at land, but he found it would be a much harder task to secure 'em at Sea. What, said he to some of the chiefest of his <hi>Tritons,</hi> what if we should build a fortification about the Ship as high as the main Mast Top all of Wool Packs, such as the Bridge of <hi>Troynovant</hi> stood upon, or else all great bags of down Feathers as they came out of <hi>Russia?</hi> The <hi>Tritons</hi> told him that truly his Invention was very good, only that such a Fortification would keep the Wind from the sails and hinder the working of the Vessel. Then do you think of a better, quo the Palatine. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that, they told him of a more usual way, which was to coil a great Anchor cable as big as his middle four or five times about, leaving room enough for his person and a Velvet Chair to sit down in. The Palatine desir'd to see such a thing, which was immediately got rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and in he went. This is pretty well, quo He, and I think pretty secure to keep a Bullet from entring: but to provide against the worst, for the best will help it self; suppose a great shot as big as a <hi>Bufola</hi>'s head should come and give the coil a gentle remove to the other side
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52570:39"/> of the Ship, and so carry Coil, <hi>Archithalassus</hi> and all into the middle of the Sea, who the Devil shall take me up again? Nay suppose that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply you should be craning me up again, and another bullet should come and break the rope of the Pully, down drops Heir apparent again, and must inevitably be drown'd before you can get another Pully ready. The best way I find is to keep out of harms way, or if the Ship do come accidentally into danger, then to shift out of that Ship into another, and so into a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third or fourth as there shall be occasion. Now what convenience is there for that? quo the <hi>Palatine.</hi> That, they told him, was easily done by means of the Long-boat. <hi>Ventre goy,</hi> quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> if I can't trust my person i' the Ship, i'le ne're trust it in the Long-boat. No, quo he again, it must be something swifter in motion than a Long-boat. I would have an Engine, like <hi>Pacolets</hi> horse, to turn with a Pin, that I might flie like a Bird from Ship to Ship. Or else such an Eagle as <hi>Ganimeds</hi> would do my business, if I could but get one as big and as tame as that. At length, after many debates and projects propos'd, it was by the <hi>Tritons</hi> concluded that he should have a place provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for him in the hole, where it would be only the trouble of Messengers to run up and down to receive his Orders. That's
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52570:39"/> the last shift upon board and board quo the <hi>Palatine;</hi> i'le e'en try the <hi>Coil</hi> first, and keep as much out of the way as I can. And then, that they might not want directions, he told them he would give them his orders from time to time, in time of Fight, by the motions of his Pendants and Streamers, and set down the sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of every motion in writing of which he would give every <hi>Triton</hi> a Copy: or else deliver them himself by word of Mouth by means of a speaking Trumpet. Thereupon a large <hi>Coil</hi> was provided with all speed; and that all the care and caution might be taken that could be, it was wash'd within side with holy water, and lin'd without side with Wafers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated after the <hi>Pagan</hi> manner, for quo they, no Bullet surely will be so prophane to touch the <hi>Pagan Eucharistia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 24.</hi> Of the desperate engagement between the <hi>Belgians</hi> and the <hi>Albionians,</hi> and of the undaunted courage of the Palatine.</head>
            <p>THe next morning the Palatine call'd for his trusty Page <hi>Epistemon;</hi> to whom, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistemon,</hi> quo he, didst thou ever read or know i' thy Life of an Heir apparent to three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms that went about to venture his Life as I do? Never that I can remember, Sir, quo <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemon;</hi> What then will future Ages think of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52570:40"/> me? quo the <hi>Palatine.</hi> They will certainly extol your undaunted courage to the skies, quo <hi>Epistemon,</hi> and look upon yee as one that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu'd neither three Kingdoms nor your Life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more than a Penn'orth of Damsons, when your Honour lay at stake. But perhaps they may blame yee for being too daring and ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. Why truly, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <hi>Hercules</hi> would have been half so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as he was, had our way of Sea fighting been then in use: Nor can I find he was ever in Expectation of three Kingdoms; a pitiful Ostler as he was, that cleans'd the <hi>Augean</hi> sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for three pence a day; and never had a suit of cloa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hs to his back, but only a Lyon's skin: What would his Club have signifi'd against a Cannon bullet? nor do I believe that <hi>Achilles</hi> would have stood still in a place, to have been knockt o' the head without being able to help himself: for there's some satisfaction in <hi>Thwick</hi> for <hi>Thwack;</hi> and a man that fights with a man fights with flesh and bones like himself: but a man is not made of mud walls to resist Cannon Bullets: and therefore he that can stand upon a Quarter deck, and bid a Cannon Bullet kiss his back-side, must certainly be much a more valiant man than ever any of the Ancient <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>'s: and that thou shalt see me do to morrow. What thô I may perhaps be out of his reach?
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52570:40"/> He that bid the <hi>Archon</hi> of <hi>Londinum</hi> kiss his tail, when he was upon the <hi>Mountains</hi> of <hi>Alta Porta,</hi> had as good a heart, as he that spoke the words to the <hi>Archon</hi>'s face. There is one thing however, for which I blame our <hi>Pagan</hi> Deities, that they never take any care of late of such Hero's as I am; whereas <hi>Jupiter</hi> sent a Dream booted and spurr'd to <hi>Agamemnon</hi> just before he went aboard the <hi>Grecian</hi> Navy, to give him a <hi>What chearho?</hi> and to encourage him to go on and fear nothing. This was some comfort to a man. But the Devil a bit will any of our Pagan <hi>Semigods</hi> come near me; althô I'le war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant yee, I have a hunder'd <hi>Ora pro nobis</hi>'s say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for me at this time. But courage, <hi>Episte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> our cause is good, and Herrings is the word: Our Seas guard us; and we must guard our Seas, that's but fair, <hi>Tit for Tat,</hi> and let all the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets in the <hi>Belgian</hi> Fleet, kiss where I sate on Sunday.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 25.</hi> Being a Continuation of things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to be left out.</head>
            <p>THis said the Palatine order'd a Gun to be fir'd, to summon the chiefest of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> aboard. To whom, most noble <hi>Tritons,</hi> quo he, I heartily thank ye for the <hi>Coil</hi> which you have provided for me; I have been in it, and find it very comfortable, and I believe 'twill prove
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52570:41"/> pretty secure. 'Twere a rare convenience for a General by Land; for then I could set it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Camels back, and ride about from Right wing to left wing as safe as a Thief in a Mill. Not but that my courage scorns such a pitiful evasion of death; but as <hi>Caesar</hi> in a storm chear'd up the skipper by telling him he carri'd <hi>Coesar</hi> and his Fortune, so noble <hi>Tritons,</hi> the Ship that carries me, carries the Fortune of <hi>Albion.</hi> For if I am lost, there's an end of a whole Royal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent. Which I may live to restore, if I can but scape these Roundheaded fiery Messengers of Death. I have heard how Industrious the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were to preserve the <hi>Fortune</hi> of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. Which made the <hi>Trojans</hi> so chary of their <hi>Palladium,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> of their <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia. Nysus</hi> had a purple lock upon which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the Fortune of <hi>Megarae;</hi> what did his Daughter do, but one night, like a Harlot as she was, she snipt off this purple lock as her Father lay asleep, and so the City was lost. I do not speak this, noble <hi>Tritons,</hi> that I fear Death; I va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue not my Life no more than I do a Cherry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone. For if you think it will be for the Glory and Welfare of <hi>Albion,</hi> do you all lie by, and I protest and vow you shall see me with this only single Ship fight the whole Navy of the <hi>Belgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> But do you on the other side consider, whether it will not be more for the general
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52570:41"/> good, that the Fortune of <hi>Albion</hi> should be safe and keep out of harm's way.</p>
            <p>Look ye, noble <hi>Triton</hi>'s, when you see a yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Streamer upon the main Top Mast head, bear to the <hi>Larboard:</hi> when you see a Sea-green Streamer, bear to the Starboard. When you see a flame colour Pendant, rake 'em fore and aft; if the Pendant be <hi>fueillemote</hi> 'tis a sign of danger, then look to the Fortune of <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> if you see a blew Streamer, lay 'em aboard; if you see a black Streamer, send in your Fire-Ships; if you see a blood red Streamer, 'tis a sign I am very angry; there's something amiss see what it is, and mend it. And when you see a green Streamer, drink brandy and refresh your selves. If a <hi>Triton</hi> happen to be desperately wounded, or kill'd give me notice by ringing the watch bell, and I'le pray for his Soul. And so, noble Tritons, every one to his command; stand to your Panpudding, let's not los<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Herring Pond for a broken shin or two: and when the battel's won, take you the blows and I'le have the Honour, and so we'le share the business between us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:52570:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 26.</hi> Of the most terrible Engagement that ever was upon the face of the Sea, and how valorously the Palatine behav'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</head>
            <p>THe Tritons being thus encourag'd, and furnish'd with Orders and Instructions, made all the sail they could to find out the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians.</hi> Nor was it long before they got sight of their whole Fleet, and no sooner had they discover'd 'em, but the <hi>Albionians</hi> gave such a shout as made the people in the Moon run out of their Houses to see what was the matter. And this was so well seconded by the Roaring and Thundring of the great Guns, that the Sun himself was in a Quandary whether he should go backward or forward. Nor was it less dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal to the Eye, to see all the four Principal Materials of the World in a Huddle together; the Ships resembling the Earth, the Guns Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting Fire, the Air condens'd into smoak, the Water under yee and the Wind i' your Tail.</p>
            <p>In this Confusion of the four Elements, the <hi>Palatine,</hi> thô not till ten <hi>Satrapes</hi> at least, and the chief <hi>Triton</hi> of the Ship upon their knees besought him to take care of the <hi>Fortune of Albion,</hi> slip't into his <hi>Coil,</hi> where he sate like a Jack Hare in his form, ever and anon waving his Scimitar, and crying, <hi>What chear ho?</hi> do we
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52570:42"/> take, or are we taken? No, Sir, quo the Seamen, but we fire like Devils. Well done, well done, quo the Palatine, what Ships are near us? They Sail, quo the Seamen, upon your Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board and Larboard like a Wall on both sides. Among 'em then, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> and with that starting up upon his Legs, &amp; spying a <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> Vessel lying like a great Whale in the Sea, without Masts or Rigging, give way, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> &amp; let me send that <hi>Skellum</hi> to Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then ordering a Broadside to be pour'd into the almost deserted Carcass of a Ship, compleated her ruine, and sent her to the Bottom of the Sea. Upon that the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men set up a <hi>Huzzah,</hi> as if the whole <hi>Belgian</hi> Fleet had been upon the Run with all the Sail they could make. Did not I tell ye, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> his Eyes flaming like two holes of a Glass house Furnace, did I not tell ye what work I'de make if once I came among 'em? Are there any more batter'd <hi>Belgians</hi> for me to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish their Destruction? The words were no sooner out of his Mouth, but by the Devils direction, came a light Horseman of a damn'd Thirty-Pounder, and took off the Head, Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Arms of three <hi>Albionian Satrapes,</hi> so near the <hi>Palatine,</hi> that the Fist of one of the Arms gave him a sound box o'the Ear, and the Brains of another beat out one of his Teeth, What Son of a Mungrel's that? quo the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52570:43"/> the Dog has turn'd my Stomach; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had puk'd a little, <hi>Ajax</hi> was never in such a fury, when he murder'd the Sheep; he bluster'd like the Northern <hi>Boreas,</hi> swell'd like an incens'd Louse in a <hi>Microscope,</hi> fum'd like a Tinker in his Ale, and Vow'd revenge upon the <hi>Belgians</hi> to the third and fourth Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till at last having quite spent himself, and finding that both Fleets having their Bellies full, had cry'd King's Truce, to take a little breath, he retir'd to his Cabin to fetch a Nap.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 27.</hi> Being a Continuation of the Bloody Engagement.</head>
            <p>THe Smoak was pretty well vanish'd, and the Sun that had been wandring in the Sky, like a benighted Traveller, for four hours together, muffl'd up in Egyptian darkness be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to see where he was, and the Infernal Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters had very near repair'd the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Sea, which had been terribly sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the violence of the Gunpowder, and the loud bellowing of the Cannon, when of a suddain, the <hi>Belgians,</hi> having refresh'd their Spirits, and rewarm'd their Courages with large Cordials of Brandy, and thinking to catch the <hi>Albionians</hi> as <hi>Moss</hi> caught his Mare, came spooning before the Wind, and bare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly with a brisk Gale upon the <hi>Albionian</hi> Fleet; but the <hi>Albionians</hi> being no less ready to receive them, in a moment there was the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52570:43"/> upon <hi>Dun</hi> again. The great Battel between the Gyants and the Gods, when Monstrous Mortals batter'd the resounding Sphears with whole Mountains at a time, and broke the Olympic Windows about the Ears of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestial Thunderer, was but a Flea-bite to this. The Concava of Heaven was but one dismal <hi>Flagellet,</hi> where the curs'd Fifty-Pounders whistl'd their Infernal Jiggs, to which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of mangl'd <hi>Phocas</hi>'s daunc'd in the bloody Air without Legs.</p>
            <p>In this astonishing Conjuncture, the Vice-<hi>Archithalassus</hi> not seeing the flame-colour'd Streamer upon the Main-Topmast-Head, sent away to the Palatine for fresh Orders and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; But the Palatine was fast asleep, like <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctavius Caesar</hi> at the Battel of <hi>Philippi.</hi> Nor durst any of the <hi>Tritons</hi> presume to wake him, nor durst any of the Vessels that hover'd about him stir from guarding the <hi>Fortune of</hi> Albion; till at length▪ Messenger after Messenger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Vice-<hi>Archithalassus,</hi> one of the <hi>Tritons</hi> knock'd at the Cabin door, first softly, then listen'd; then harder, then listen'd again. But nobody wak'd, nobody stirr'd: presently comes another, and another and another Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger, to tell the Palatine the Vice-<hi>Architha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lassus</hi> was Wounded, and they open'd the Door and went in. But Heavens! in what a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52570:44"/> Consternation were they then? They drew the Curtains, lookt into the Bed, and under the Bed, and over the Bed, search'd every Corner and Cranny of the Room, but no <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> was to be found. They saw the Cabin tite, the Window shut, and the Bed-cloaths un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing'd, and what Devil had carry'd him away a Pick-back, they could not imagine. Well, quo they, farewel Victory, the Fortune of <hi>England</hi> is lost. No, no, quo another. I'le warrant ye for a <hi>Gravesend</hi> Toast we shall see him again: this is only the Kindness of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; there is some perillous Hour at hand, and some of the Pagan Deities have brought him a <hi>Gyges</hi>'s Ring to preserve him Invisible, till the danger be over. Now I'le be hang'd if he ben't i' the Cabin, but if he should speak, the Vertue of the Ring would be lost, and that he knows, and therefore does wisely to hold his Tongue. Did not <hi>Venus</hi> hide <hi>Aeneas</hi> in a Cloud when he was in the same Danger? and do you think there are not some of the Female-Pagan-Goddesses that love him as well as <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> lov'd her Darling?</p>
            <p>Now tho' it were not altogether so as the <hi>Triton</hi> said, yet it was somewhat like it. For afterwards it was found out, and if it be not, it ought to be recorded for one of the greatest Miracles that ever were known since the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Antichrist.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="chapter">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:52570:44"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 28.</hi> Of the Miraculous Preservation of the Palatine, which surpasses all belief.</head>
            <p>FOr so it fell out, that one of the Pagan Goddesses, some say, <hi>Sancta Agatha,</hi> some say the Egyptian <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> who of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Harlot, became a Pagan Goddess; some say one, and some say another; 'tis not a Pin matter which; but one there was, who whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther she were tyr'd with the continual <hi>Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> of the <hi>Astopian Raminogrobis</hi>'s, or whether it were out of her peculiar Compassion to the Palatine, is not material to our History, came down from her Celestial Mansion, with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on but her Shift and her Slippers, which made some believe she was a Kin to the Silver sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p sho'd <hi>Icis</hi> that was courted by <hi>Zephyrus;</hi> this Goddess, I say, well-knowing the danger that near at hand threatned the <hi>Palatine,</hi> and finding him so carelesly asleep, took him up in her Arms (for your Pagan Goddesses are all Strappers) carried him out of the Cabin Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow invisible, and conveighing him in again at one of the Port-holes, lugg'd him down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hold, and after she had laid him upon the Ballast, upon the very same Bed of Roses upon which <hi>Venus</hi> laid <hi>Adonis,</hi> cover'd him with the hinder part of her shift, which she tore off for that purpose, and so leaving him,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52570:45"/> bare-breech to the <hi>Coelum Empiraeum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She nickt it, you'l say exactly. For at the same time the <hi>Belgian Archithalassus,</hi> mov'd by the Instigation of the Devil, could find, or at least was resolv'd to find out nobody else to win Grinning Honour by, but the <hi>Architha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lassus</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi> Now this <hi>Belgian Architha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lassus</hi> was just such another as <hi>Prometheus,</hi> who they say, cover'd a whole Acre of Ground when he lay upon his Belly. And it seems he had made a Vow, if he took the <hi>Palatine</hi> alive, to shut him up in an Iron Cage, and shew him about the Cities of <hi>Batavia,</hi> as <hi>Tamerlain</hi> did <hi>Bajazet;</hi> and for a Memorial of his Victory, to hire four Astrologers to take down <hi>Arion</hi>'s <hi>Dolphin</hi> from the Sky, and put up a Barrel of red Herrings in the room. Thus resolv'd, he bore up to the <hi>Palatine</hi> with all the Sail he could make, and a resolution to Board him, and do such farther M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>schief as the Devil should put into his thoughts. But curst Cows have short Horns. For the <hi>Triton Thims</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving the <hi>Belgian Archithalassus</hi>'s wicked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, strook in with his <hi>Spitfire</hi> between the <hi>Palatine</hi> and him; and as the <hi>Pagan Goddesses</hi> would have it, plac'd a great Shot so exactly between Wind and Water, that by force it enter'd the Powder Room without a Writ in <hi>Withernam.</hi> Presently (for there was no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevy
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52570:45"/> i' the case) there was the Devil and all to do. The Bullet set the Powder a fire, the Powder set the Ship a fire, and in a moment sent the <hi>Belgian Archithalassus</hi> to Heaven in a fiery Chariot, with a Silver Tankard in his hand, to present <hi>Peter</hi> the Door-keeper. Tho' if any man ought to have gone first to Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, the Belgian <hi>Archithalassus</hi> did; confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how he stunk of Sulphur and Brimston; perfumes the most ungrateful in the world to the Inhabitants of the <hi>Empyraean</hi> Mansions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 29.</hi> How the Palatine wak'd and was found again to the great Joy of those that beheld him.</head>
            <p>THe Pagan Goddess, that stay'd in the Orb of the Moon, all this while, to see the Event of things, perceiving the Danger was over, and hearing what a lamentable stir the <hi>Phocasses</hi> kept for their <hi>Archithalassus,</hi> darted again from the Sky like a Spider upon a Fly, or like the <hi>Turcoman</hi> Dancer upon the Ropes from the Top of his Pole, and finding the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> still in a sweet sleep, took him up in her Arms, and as a Midwife carries an Infant to the Font; convey'd him back again to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, and laid him where she found him. Soon after the horrid noise in the Ship wak'd him, and out he came rubbing his Eyes upon the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52570:46"/> Quarter Deck, to the no less joy than amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all that beheld him. Welcom from the other World, Noble <hi>Palatine,</hi> quo the Chief <hi>Triton</hi> of the Ship. From the other World indeed, quo the <hi>Palatine;</hi> for I ha' been with Angels and Arch-Angels, and Pagan Gods and Goddesses, and I know not who my self. We thought so, quo the <hi>Triton,</hi> for we have been seeking for ye these two hours, and could not find ye neither high nor low: But did ye meet no body upon the Road as ye came down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? How so? quo the Palatine. Marry, quo the <hi>Triton,</hi> here came the Belgian <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalassus</hi> to enquire for ye, and we told him we thought you were gone into the other World; whereupon he immediately took post with all his Ships Company, and went after ye: and with that he told the Palatine the whole Story of the blowing up of the Belgian <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chithalassus. Vertue Goy,</hi> quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> I would not have been here for a Million; for I should have been all for grapling, and Board<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; my Fingers would have been itching to have had a single Touch with my Brother <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chithalassus,</hi> and so we should have spilt an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of Christian Blood between us, when the Business was done a shorter and more compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way. I have known an <hi>Epitome</hi> do much better than the Volume at large. For example,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52570:46"/> there is <hi>Ashmole</hi>'s History of our Order, would be far better Epitomiz'd. So the most Compendious way of sending an Enemy out of the World is the best; and saves an <hi>Architha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lassus</hi> the Chargeable Expence of a Funeral. Then for the Honour of the Action, who dares refuse it me so long as I live, and I'le make it pass currant in future Story to boot.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Belgians,</hi> having lost their <hi>Archithalassus,</hi> and some three or four more of their biggest <hi>Towzers,</hi> made all the Sail they could to their own Coasts, and the Palatine was glad he was rid of 'em so. Nevertheless, the <hi>Belgians</hi> were so obstinate, that they would not yield the Palatine the Victory, unless he would come to such and such terms; for as for the blowing up of their <hi>Archithalassus,</hi> it was a Chance that might have happen'd to the <hi>Palatine</hi> as well as to them, and therefore was not to be reckon'd among their Losses by downright Thumping and fair Blows. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it was concluded that two of the most eminent <hi>Tritons</hi> in each Fleet, should be made choice of, one for the <hi>Albionians,</hi> and another for the <hi>Belgians,</hi> and that these two should throw most at three throws upon three Dice, for the Glory of the Day. He that was for the <hi>Belgians</hi> threw first Six, Eight and Five, then two Fives and a Tray; and in the last
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52570:47"/> place, Aumes Ace and a Duce. He that was for the <hi>Albionians,</hi> threw first Two Sixes and a Four, then Six, Five and Four, and lastly three Duces, and so the <hi>Albionians</hi> and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine had the Honour of the Victory.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Ch. 30.</hi> Of the Great Rejoycing and Triumphing in the City of <hi>Troy-Novant,</hi> for the great Victory obtain'd against the <hi>Belgians,</hi> and of the great Honours done the <hi>Palatine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe News of this great Victory being spread through all the Streets of <hi>Troy-Novant,</hi> as soon the Palatine's Fame fill'd all the Coffee-Houses of that spacious City. He that enter'd into any Discourses, but of the Palatine's renowned Actions, had a Dish of the Stygian Liquor flung in his Face. There they decreed the Number of the Belgian <hi>Towzers</hi> Sunk and Taken, of the <hi>Triton</hi>'s kill'd, of the <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cas</hi>'s Slain and Pris'ners: and having discover'd in the Mists and Fumes of Tabacco and <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bean-broth, a Victory much more signal than was reported, Poor <hi>Fame</hi> was Jilted, Whor'd, Plagu'd, Pox'd, and Hagg'd for being too sparing of her Lungs, and partial to the Palatine. They bid her sell her pitiful pimping squ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aling Quail-Pipe to the Shewers of Strange Fish, and buy her a Speaking Trumpet of Fifty yards long, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:52570:47"/> keep the four Winds in Pay to blow it; in regard the <hi>Palatines</hi> Renown would find 'em all work enough.</p>
            <p>I wonder, crys one, whether the Palatine will make any Publick Entry through the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? 'Tis order'd already crys another, that he shall ride from <hi>Julius Caesar</hi>'s Tower to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Regalis</hi> in the <hi>Royal Charles,</hi> drawn by Six h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dred forty eight Sea-Horses, with every one a Mermaid upon his Back, and <hi>Neptune</hi> himself is to be the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stillion; and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Grocers are forbid to sell the Boys any Gun-Powder to prevent the throwing of Squibs.</p>
            <p>This is all too little, cryes a grave Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with a Strawberry Countenance, I would have the same Honours decreed the <hi>Palatine,</hi> as the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> decreed <hi>Caligula</hi> for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Souldiers Helmets with <hi>Cockle▪ Shells;</hi> for I believe this to be as terrible a Fight as ever that was. Terrible! Sir, quo another, I was in it, and the Devil choak me, if ever any pot boyl'd as the Sea did for six Hours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. To confirm what you say, cry'd ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I had one of the great Iron Bullets that Sunk the <hi>Zealander</hi> of Sixty four Guns, to Dinner to day; and may I never swallow more, if it did not eat as tender as a Cabbidge. Judge you then of the stupendious Valour and Prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ess of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> that could endure in such a Brunt as this, and never Flinch.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:52570:48"/>
            <p>The <hi>Albi, Regalians</hi> met him upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Thamesis,</hi> with fifteen hund'red Painted Barges, singing <hi>Io Triumphe;</hi> call'd him the Son of <hi>Neptune,</hi> which the <hi>Palatine</hi> scrupl'd not to owne, with great Admiration of himself; and the first thing they Presented him with, was a Crown of Gold Tinsel, made in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Garland of <hi>Sea Holly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Archon</hi> of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> also went to Congratulate his safe return, and made hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Present of a vast March-pane Man of War, Swimming in an Ocean of Custard. His Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers surrounded him, his Parasites encircl'd him, and his Buffoons clung about him, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the <hi>Jason</hi> of his Time, and extolling his Valour to the Sphear of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and the two Muses <hi>Melpomene</hi> and <hi>Clio</hi> were at work Night and Day to make him Panegyricks. And no question but had he accompany'd his Brother <hi>Archithalassus,</hi> and dy'd upon the spot, he had won immortal Honour, and had been translated into the Upper Regions, and Catalogu'd among the <hi>Pagan Gods</hi> and <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desses,</hi> like the <hi>Roman</hi> Imperators. At length to compleat all the rest, Addresses also came from <hi>Longtail</hi> and <hi>Bobtail</hi> from every Corner of the Kingdom, to thank him for <hi>what the Cat l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st in the Mault.</hi> And the <hi>Phanatick Philosophers,</hi> call'd <hi>Virtuosi,</hi> presented him with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52570:48"/> an Engine to make white black, and black white, when ever he should have occasion to use it.</p>
            <p>So that the <hi>Belgians,</hi> hearing what a Clutter the <hi>Albionians</hi> made of their Victory which they had got but by one spot of a die, they fell a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Bonfires and Fire-works like mad, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing and triumphing for the great Victory ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd over the <hi>Albionians</hi> on their side. Which was a great ecclipse to the Palatines Honour: for all the <hi>Europaean</hi> Princes perceiving so light a feather turn'd the Scales, when ever they met together drew cuts which side to believe, and if at any time, the Palatines Agents made boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Masters Prowess in any of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, they said nothing, but nodded their heads and laid their fore fingers upon their noses, and 'tis said that the <hi>Waywode</hi> of <hi>Ditto</hi> when he had read the <hi>Cologne</hi> Corant hang'd himself, for being so much mistaken in his <hi>Politicks</hi> as to send his Envoy to Congratulate the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> success.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 31.</hi> How Peace ensu'd, and then War, and then Peace and then War again between the <hi>Albionians</hi> and the <hi>Belgians,</hi> and how the Palatine cut the Gordian Knot.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Palatine</hi> thus finding it was not so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie a thing to destroy the <hi>Belgians,</hi> as he
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52570:49"/> thought it had been, sent to the King of the <hi>Astopians</hi> who was a rank <hi>Pagan,</hi> desiring him that they two might lay their heads together to consider what was farther to be done. And in Conclusion they made the strictest league of Friendship together that ever was known. For after they had twisted both their Interests to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with two great Iron wheels, as close and as firm as the strongest Cable rope in the world, and so long as to reach from <hi>Lutetia</hi> to <hi>Troy-Novant,</hi> the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> caus'd fifteen <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clops</hi>'s to fasten one end of the Interest-Cable to the Region of his Heart with twenty Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nails such as they drive into the Ribs of a great Ship, forc'd in with Massie Anchor Hammers; and the Palatine order'd the other end of the Interest-Cable to be fasten'd in like manner to the Region of his Heart, so that it was impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for either to stir unless they went jointly together. After this the <hi>Palatine</hi> sold the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version and Remainder of the three Kingdoms of <hi>Albion, Caledonia</hi> and <hi>Hibernia,</hi> with all the Giblets thereto belonging, after the King of <hi>Albions</hi> decease, to the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and his Heirs for ever; Provided that the Palatine should hold them in Vassalage of the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> during his own Life. On the other side it was covenanted and agreed that the King of <hi>Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> should furnish the <hi>Palatine</hi> with whatever
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:52570:49"/> summ or summs of Money he should ask or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to be expended all toward the Extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the <hi>Christians</hi> from the face of the Earth. All which being approv'd and consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, a brace of Envoys were dispatch'd to the Emperor of the Infernal Regions for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Articles under the great Seal of the Bottomless Pit: and withal to request such farther Assistance from his <hi>Plutonian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> as the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the Palatine should from time to time desire.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Belgians</hi> having notice of this Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strial and Infernal Combination against them, immediately enter'd into a strict confederacy with the King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> the <hi>Arragonian</hi> Monarch, and the <hi>Christians</hi> of <hi>Albion,</hi> and for more surety bound themselves all together in a bundle, like the King of <hi>Scythia</hi>'s Emblem of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, with the bark of a Cornet Tree, &amp; so fasten'd the Knot, that there was neither Beginning nor End to be seen; so that it was thought impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for all the wit of man to untie it.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the Palatine were strangely consternated at this <hi>Association;</hi> for the one foresaw, that unless he could unloose it some way or other, he should never attain to the Universal Monarchy of <hi>Europe;</hi> and the other for the same Reason, despair'd of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the Christians. Presently the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:52570:50"/> having heard of the Story of <hi>Alexander</hi> was for cutting it; withal he told the King of <hi>Astopia,</hi> that he had a Lord that was the best at paring of Pippins in the World, and that he would send him to take his opportunity to give it a sliver; And indeed that slie <hi>Necromancer</hi> gave it such a gash, that it hung meerly by one Thread. So that the <hi>Palatine</hi> having thus ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Knot useless, the King of the <hi>Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians</hi> and he resolv'd to set upon the <hi>Belgians</hi> a second time. But whether it were that the <hi>Palatine</hi> did not like the sport of his own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or that having bought a hunting Nagg of a Lady of Quality, and having sprain'd the lower▪ Vertebraes of his Chine in leaping after a Buck, he could not be there; so it was, that the Care and Management of that War was committed to others, and the <hi>Palatine</hi> only sate in a Beacon, and look'd on; so that we have nothing more to say to that Affair.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 32.</hi> How the Palatine follow'd the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Nero</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was Milk and Honey to the Palatine, that he had found out away to set the Christians, as he was in good hopes, at a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual enmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y one with another, and to see them lambasting, thrashing and thumping each other as they did for a few <hi>China</hi> Dishes, and Petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:52570:50"/> Silks, or as if the Pepper of <hi>India</hi> had been the <hi>summum bonum</hi> of all Mankind. The <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> bless'd themselves to hear that two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should so dismally mangle one another for the seasoning of a Venson Pasty. But the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> and the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> had their Ends, and car'd not thô Heaven and Earth had been clapt together like two Furmity Dishes. But nothing afflicted the <hi>Palatine</hi> so much as to see the flourishing Condition of the great City of <hi>Troynovant,</hi> abounding in wealth and vast num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Christians. He remembred their large Contributions of Thimbles and Bodkins against the late King of <hi>Albion,</hi> and dreaded nothing more than that the Riches and Populousness of that vast City, would be the only obstruction of all his deep laid contrivances against the Christians. He knew the Devil himself could never make the Earth gape wide enough to swallow it up. What way therefore to level it as smooth as the back of his hand, he could not for his Soul devise. To those that gave him Advice to fire it, he made answer, that he kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w the story of the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> how she set her Nest a Fire and reviv'd again; that the <hi>Pagans</hi> were the better and came out the more refin'd for going into Purgatory, that the World was to be renew'd by fire, and therefore fire was not an Element to be trusted in an Affair of so
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:52570:51"/> great Importance. For quo the Palatine, I would have shav'd it from the ground as clean as a man's Beard from his Chin with a Razor, and so thrown into the middle of the Sea. Then proceeding, we all know, quo the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> there is a way of smothering Bees to Death. Now a great City is but a great Bee-hive, and the People are but a vast number of Bees with a great many Drones mix'd among 'em: Why then might there not be a project found out to smother these Bees of Christians to death in their Combs with moist brown Paper and old Cards? It would be a double Pleasure to see the Christians perish, and perish in Torment. What d' ye say, Son's of <hi>Loyola?</hi> you are old Dogs at mischief, go and lay your heads together. For this great City sticks i' my Stomack, past all the <hi>Oxymel Squilliticum</hi> or Antimony in the World to fetch it up, <hi>Emou zontos gaia mictheto pyri</hi> is the Word. So said <hi>Nero</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Rome,</hi> and so say I. The Loyolists applauded the magnanimous Resolution of the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>latine,</hi> but withal they told him there was no Element but fire would do the Business: for that they had got such a Composition that water would inflame, but never quench, and that they would undertake to do it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="chapter">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:52570:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ch. 33.</hi> More of this and something else.</head>
            <p>NO sooner was the business concluded, but an Envoy arriv'd from the Emperour of the Infernal Regions, who was presently admitted to his private Audience. In the first place he told the <hi>Palatine</hi> that his Master had sent a hundred waggon-loads of thanks per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd with brimstone for his great care of the General concern; That he highly approv'd the design of firing <hi>Troy▪ Novant,</hi> and that for the carrying on of the business, his Master had sent him twenty Fly-boats of right Infernal <hi>Bitumen</hi> that would catch like tinder, and flame like burnt brandy; encouraging the Palatine withal not to fear the discovery of his name, for that his Master would cast such a mist be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Eyes of the People that they should never be able to read it tho 'twere writ in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie's</hi> Letters. Care was also taken, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch away another Envoy to King <hi>Eolus</hi> to desire him to chain up the <hi>North Wind</hi> to the <hi>Pole Arti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> and let loose a strong easterly gale: and to prevent rain, that the Region of the Air might be brusht and swept so clean that there might not a Cloud be seen in the Sky. Others there were in the Confederacy that propounded the sending of a Courrier to <hi>Vulcan,</hi> to desire him to send them his great pair of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:52570:52"/> Smith's Bellows. But there was one of the <hi>Loyolists</hi> more cunning than all the rest, who advis'd the Palatine to save all this charges, for that he knew a <hi>Loyalist</hi> that had all the Winds in a bag made of a flead Dolphins Skin, and that by the force of certain charms that he knew how to mumble, he could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the winds to blow as he listed himself. I believe, quo the Palatine to the <hi>Loyolist,</hi> that your Friend may have such a bag, and I like it very well, but I love to be sure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will send for <hi>Vulcans</hi> great Bellows what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they cost me.</p>
            <p>And it will be very requisite, cryed another who was one of the chief of the <hi>Loyolists</hi> that we conjure up a certain number of <hi>Miphosto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pholus</hi>'s (having whole Legions at Command) to fly about in the Air and daub the outsides of all the Houses, Temples and Steeples, with <hi>Naphta</hi> and <hi>Bitumen.</hi> Now <hi>Naphta</hi> was the Invention of that famous Witch <hi>Medea;</hi> and the Nature of it is such that whatever is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smear'd with it, catches immediately if it come but within sight of Fire or the Sun, and burns beyond any possibility of quenching it. And <hi>Bitumen</hi> has another quality to draw fire to it, and set the very Air of Fire. Now of two such Infernal Ingredients as these was made up the composition of the <hi>Paynim</hi> fire-balls,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:52570:52"/> and the Houses were besmeared by the <hi>Mipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stofusus</hi>'s, with such Inchantments as these that the City of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> should burn for three days together. For not only the <hi>Miphostofus</hi>'s flew about invisibly in the day time; daub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and plaistring the Houses with their Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Birdlime, but the <hi>Panim Loyolists</hi> sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their Emissaries in the night time laden with this Infernal Morter to stick it up and down wherever they could find any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustible Matter. And indeed never did any Conflagrations of whole Cities so nearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble one another as those of old <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Troy Novant.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 34.</hi> Of the Great Similitude in every particular between the <hi>Two</hi> dismal Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grations of Old <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>New Troy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Conflagration followd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Tacitus Annal. lib. 15.</note> by chance or by the Treachery of the Prince is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain; for Authors have delivered both. It was begun in that part of the City where those sorts of Wares and Merchandizes lay that were most apt to feed the flames. The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all in Consternation and Ambiguous what to avoid, what course to take, some fill'd up the Streets, others lay scatter'd in the Fields adjoyning, wringing their hands and bewailing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:52570:53"/> their irrecoverable losses; Others that labour'd to quench the Raging Flames, toyl'd and moyl'd in vain, while the <hi>Panim</hi> Emissaries publickly nourished the Conflagration with fresh fuel, and being apprehended, boasted the Protection of him that set them at work. So that afterwards tho the Prince seem'd to take a great deal of care of the Distressed Multitude, yet it signify'd nothing, in regard there was a Rumour spread, that while the City was all on flame, he enter'd into his <hi>Domestick Theatre,</hi> and sang the burning of <hi>Troy.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 35.</hi> Where the Comparison ends.</head>
            <p>WHen the Genius of <hi>Albion,</hi> heard this Doleful Relation uttered from the lips of the Venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> Alas poor <hi>Troy-No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> said he, how like was thy calamity to this! The King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the <hi>Palatine</hi> in imitation of <hi>Nero,</hi> conspiring thy ruin, and to lay thee in ashes call up for assistance from the Infernal Regions; and all the while thou burnst, they Kiss and Court, and with their fair <hi>Poppaea's</hi> wantonnize.</p>
            <p>At length when <hi>Brontes, Steropes</hi> and <hi>Pyrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had quite tired themselves with blowing <hi>Vulcans</hi> Massie Bellow's till they could blow no longer, and the devouring flames had gorg'd themselves upon the Stately Structures of <hi>Troy-Novant,</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:52570:53"/> which now lay all in ashes, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the Infernal Regions, sent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way his Grand Visier <hi>Moloch</hi> to the <hi>Astopian</hi> King and the <hi>Palatine,</hi> to congratulate the happy success of their design, assuring them that it was not out of any disaffection to their cause, but only because it was not in his power, that he did not turn the soyl upon which <hi>Troy▪ No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> stood into a lake like that of old <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> to the end it might never be built upon again. Withal the Lord <hi>Moloch</hi> had in charge to bid the <hi>Astopian</hi> King and the <hi>Palatine</hi> have a care of the <hi>Grand Senate</hi> of <hi>Albion;</hi> for that he foresaw they would in a short time rebuild it again, unless by their Prudence and Interest they could dissolve that detested Nest of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and send the Birds to <hi>Avernus;</hi> and last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he bid them be sure to lay the Burning of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> upon the Christians themselves, as the Emperor <hi>Nero</hi> laid the firing of <hi>Old Rome</hi> upon the Children of <hi>Israel;</hi> all which the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the Palatine promis'd to use their utmost endeavour to see done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Imperial Majesties Directions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="chapter">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:52570:54"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</hi> Of the Great joy at the Imperial Court of <hi>Gehenna</hi> for the Burning of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> and how the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the <hi>Palatine</hi> triumph'd over a Map of the Ruines.</head>
            <p>SO soon as the <hi>Sultan</hi> of <hi>Gehenna</hi> had dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched away his Embassador <hi>Moloch,</hi> he call'd together the rest of his sooty Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, <hi>Baal Peor, Bell and the Dragon, Ashta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth, Satan, Osiris, Thamuz, Lucifer, Belzebub, Gerion, Orcus, Tartarus,</hi> Madam <hi>Dagon,</hi> the Lady <hi>Hecate,</hi> Madam <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mesis,</hi> and some hundreds more too long to remember, who being all assembled together, the <hi>Sultan</hi> being mounted upon his Imperial Throne, <q rend="margQuotes">Right Trusty and well beloved Cousins and Counsellers, quo he, it is our will and pleasure, that there shall be a Publick <hi>Jubile</hi> of twelve years throughout all our Dominions, for the Burning of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Albion;</hi> a spacious Nest of <hi>Christians</hi> that disturb'd my Ears more than all the world beside, with their six a Clock Bells and their three a Clock Bells, and their first and second Peals in one Temple or other all the Week long: I could not sleep in the morning, nor take a Nap after dinner for their j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngling the people together to worship my Grand Enemy.</q>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:52570:54"/> They hated our beloved, the Scarlet <hi>Lais</hi> of <hi>Babylon:</hi> They abominated our trusty Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Vicegerent <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and would not suffer a <hi>Panim</hi> Priest to rest within their Walls, but hang'd up all those our true and faithful servants where ever they found 'em: And lastly they sheltered all the Enemies of the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the Palatine of <hi>Eboracum,</hi> who were the Grand Protectors of our Grand <hi>Babylonian</hi> Council <hi>de Propaganda fide;</hi> For these reasons we put it into the hearts of the <hi>Astopian</hi> Prince and the Palatine to level it with the Earth, and now our Councels have succeeded, by our great River <hi>Styx</hi> we will be merry. Is <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> laid in ashes, quo he? And with that he fell a laughing for an hour together so loud, that he made the Pillars of Hell Shake. And it has been since reported by several Ghosts of the deceas'd that have been forc'd to return to the Earth to tell where they had hid their money, that they never saw such feasting in Hell in their lives. Millions of Dishes of thirty acres in circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of one sort of Food heap'd up to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that it was as much as a Legion of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils could do to carry one. In some a Million of Black Bulls; in others as many Black Dogs; in others as many Hogs of <hi>Genesareth;</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whole Mountains of the Entrails of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:52570:55"/> Heifers covered over with fat and oyl: In others whole Woods of Cypress, Ram's thorn, Daffadillies and Juniper for Sallets. What they wanted in Wine they made up in Brandy and Coffee, of which the Emperor of <hi>Gehenna</hi> would make nothing to drink off at a draught a Gold Beaker as big as the Tun of <hi>Heidelbergh.</hi> And thus they continued Revelling and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baushing in Hell for three years together, till hearing that the Inhabitants of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> were resolv'd to rebuild their City, and that the Grand Senate of <hi>Albion</hi> had so order'd it, that the City was like to be ten times more beautiful than ever it was, the <hi>Sultan</hi> of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna</hi> fell into such a violent and excessive rage, that he threw the Tables one way, the Dishes another, here lay a Mountain of Green Lizards and Vipers Fricass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, with a Morass of Sauce about it, and for above thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Leagues in compass, nothing but <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Towers of Diabolical Viands, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigable Lakes of Burning Brandy, prepar'd to have been quaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off in <hi>Snap-dragons,</hi> had the <hi>Triumphant Debaush</hi> gone on, insomuch that Hell it self seem'd to lye in ruines; and they were forc'd to send for the Great Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinger <hi>Hercules</hi> to take away the Devil's leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and make the Roads of that part of Hell passable: Which was said to be the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:52570:55"/> last and most difficult of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> and the Palatine having gotten a draught of the City Ruins, pleased themselves with the sight of it, and were very merry upon it for eight and forty hours together. Where was it the fire first seiz'd, quo the King of <hi>Astopia?</hi> Here, quo the <hi>Palatine.</hi> What place was that call'd? quo the King. <hi>Pudding Lane,</hi> quo the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine.</hi> Pudding, that's to say <hi>Boudin</hi> in the Language of <hi>Astopia. Hoh,</hi> quo the King of <hi>Astopia,</hi> 'Twas the right way of well feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to begin with the Pudding. All herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, quo the Pala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, liv'd your great dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in Pitch, Tar, Rosin, and such like Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustible Matters, which being melted by the violence of the flames and mix'd with the Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel water, You would have laught to see how the slaves basted their own houses. 'Twas yet but an Infant of a Conflagration, and therefore 'twas fit to feed it with Spoon meat.—But what place was this, quo the King of <hi>Astopia?</hi> This house quo the <hi>Palatine</hi> belong'd to the <hi>Easterling</hi> Merchants, and was call'd the <hi>Steel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi>—Excellent well, quo the King of <hi>Astopia.</hi> 'Twill signifie nothing when I come to be Master of the <hi>Hanse-Towns.</hi> Here, quo the Palatine, stood a famous <hi>Rhenish-Wine</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:52570:56"/> and the Flames were mad to be at the Old-Hock. They knew what was good for themselves, for <hi>Vin Ardant</hi> in your Language is <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> in ours. <hi>Bon prou leur face,</hi> quo the King of <hi>Astopia;</hi> They that won't drink when they 're a dry, let 'em die for thirst in a Mildamm. 'Tis very true, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> and here stood the <hi>Mony-changers</hi> Street—vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly call'd, the Street of the <hi>Lombards. A beau feu bel Argent</hi> quo the <hi>Astopian Hero;</hi> 'Twas the true way of making <hi>aurum Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile;</hi> I'de rather the Devil should have money than my Subjects.—But what's written there? The <hi>Bourse Royal,</hi> quo the Palatine, <hi>Ah—parbleu</hi> quo the King of <hi>Astopia, Le Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chand n'espargne nuls;</hi> The Marchant spares none; why should we spare them? And so, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> the Flames ran on till they came hither to <hi>Pye-Corner. Coign du Pastè, Coign du Pastè!</hi> Quo the <hi>Astopian Hector, Bougre de les Lourdauts de Flammes,</hi> did they leave that bit for manners? And so they came along down hither and burnt <hi>Bridewel</hi> which <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th built, and here again his own Chappel. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goy O LeGrandVoleur del'Eglise, Le grand Enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi de nostre</hi> St. <hi>Pere</hi> quo the <hi>Hector</hi> of <hi>Astopia,</hi> I would have sworn the Flames had been all Hugonots, had they spar'd that Hereticks Monuments. And all the way Sir, quo the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:52570:56"/>
               <hi>Palatine,</hi> the <hi>Thirstie</hi> Conflagration drank burnt Sack and Claret by whole Hoggsheads.—<hi>A beau feu, beau retour,</hi> Tit for Tat, quo the <hi>Astopian Monarch;</hi> There was no reason such a great Sty of unconverted <hi>Christians</hi> should want burnt Wine at it's Funeral. But what are all these Huge Gobbets remaining? Morsel's for another festival, quo the <hi>Palatine, Ah Morbleu,</hi> quo the King of <hi>Astopia, Mal fait qui ne parfait,</hi> Discontinuance of the Work dishonours the Enterprize. You see how I make whole Countries flame before me, fire whole Provinces, &amp; make Depopulation her self march before me in a fiery Chariot. <hi>Tout beau,</hi> fair and softly quo the <hi>Palatine, Rome</hi> was not burnt in a day.—And yet I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that such a Holocaust of Humane Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations was ever offer'd to any of the <hi>Panim</hi> Deities by any of the <hi>Panims</hi> before. If the Progress answer the beginning, quo the <hi>Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian Monarch.</hi> I think the Devil grew compassionate, quo the Palatine, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress was no better, I'm sure 'twas no fault of our's; for to our knowledge all our Guards were diligently employ'd to hinder the Caitiffs from removing their goods, it being our aim that their whole Estates should perish in the same fires with their Houses. The same care
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:52570:57"/> was also taken to see to the dismissing and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging several that were taken fomenting and adding fuel to the flame. And the slaves were order'd to carry all they took to <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> and the Castle of <hi>San Jacomo,</hi> not to secure them, but reward them, and give them an opportunity to escape. If the Emperour of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna</hi> turn'd Milk-sop what could we help it?</p>
            <p>Here they both brake off a bruptly, not but that their discourse was much longer, and their joy unspeakable, but the Palatine was call'd off by a Messenger from his <hi>Sultaness,</hi> who was retir'd to her Chamber with certain of the Loyolists to sing a <hi>Black Santum</hi> of praise and Thanksgiving to the Pagan Goddesses for so good and prosperous a Beginning.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 37.</hi> How the <hi>Palatine</hi> and the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> pursu'd their design of destroying the <hi>Belgians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHile the devouring Flames were thus reducing <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> to Ash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, the Palatine had so contriv'd it that there was at the same time a new War broke out between the <hi>Belgians</hi> and the <hi>Albionians.</hi> For it was so order'd and complotted between the Pagan <hi>Palatine</hi> and the Heathen <hi>Astopian,</hi> that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:52570:57"/> while the <hi>Belgians</hi> and <hi>Albionians</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in a bloody War by Sea, that the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Flames should banquet upon the Inland Strength and Riches of <hi>Albion</hi> at the same time that the <hi>Astopian Hector</hi> was ransacking the Bowels of the lower <hi>Belgium.</hi> Which they thought the surest way to ruine both the one and the other. One thing however very much troubl'd the <hi>Palatine,</hi> that be thought to have been <hi>Archithalassus</hi> again in this same se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond War. But the <hi>Albi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nians</hi> offended at his ill and dishonourable Conduct of the first war, exclaim'd against him and would by no means suffer him to go. So that the King of <hi>Albion</hi> was forc'd to keep him at home under the specious pretence of his care not to hazard the <hi>Fortune</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi> However to content him, he gave him full power to rule the roast in his Counsels at home as he pleas'd himself. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this great Authority which was put into his Hands, the <hi>Palatine</hi> was not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd, but fum'd and foam'd because he was not made <hi>Archithalassus.</hi> For the Soldan of <hi>Albion</hi> had made two <hi>Archithalassus</hi>'s in his stead, the <hi>Teutonic</hi> Prince and the Devonian Knight, who were right valorous Champions, which gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d the <hi>Palatine</hi> to that degree that he studi'd all manner of ways to eclipse their
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:52570:58"/> Glory and render their Prowess and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ineffectual. To this purpose he consulted his grand Counsel of <hi>Loyolists,</hi> who advis'd him to divide the <hi>Albionian</hi> Navy, thereby to expose the whole to utter Ruin. For he well knew that such was the magnanimous Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both the <hi>Archithalassus</hi>'s, that being both united they would certainly return with Glory and Triumph to his Eternal Infamy, but being separated and overpower'd by number, they might become a prey to the Enemy, which was the only thing he wish'd for. To this purpose he goes to the famous Enchantress <hi>Circe,</hi> and Conjures her to use all her charms to lay the King of <hi>Albion</hi> in a deep Trance, which it was no difficult thing for her to do, in regard she was both beautiful and fair, and greatly admir'd by the King of <hi>Albion:</hi> and then having the Command of all things in his own power, under pretence that his Sultaness long'd, he sent away the strictest Orders imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the <hi>Teutonic Prince</hi> to take along with him the best half of the <hi>Albionian</hi> Navy, and sail away forthwith to the Bay of <hi>Cantabria</hi> to gather Spanish O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sters and <hi>Sea Fanns.</hi> Now so it fell out, as if the Devil and the Oracle of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> had been in the Loyolists, that the <hi>Belgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> having notice of the <hi>Teutonice Prince</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:52570:58"/> thus sent of a Sleeveless Errand, came up with their whole Navy of a suddain and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded the Devonian Knight. Heaven's bless us! You would have thought all the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of the upper Regions had been tumbling about your Ears. For the <hi>Devonian Knight,</hi> more regarding his Honour than his safety, fought like a Dragon; but being over-power'd by number, he was forc'd to make a retreating fight, leaving one of the best of all his great Thunderers behind him; and worse it had been, but that the <hi>Teutonic Prince,</hi> being adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis'd of the bloody Engagement, bid all the Spanish Periwinkles go to the Devil, and flew with all the sail he could make to the rescue of the <hi>Devonian Knight.</hi> But when the Devil and Treachery conspire together, who the Devil can help it? For when the <hi>Teutonic</hi> Prince, and the Devonian Knight were joyn'd and thought to have scour'd off the <hi>Belgians</hi> the next day, <hi>Belzebub</hi> had stole away all their Powder; and before they could get more, the <hi>Belgians</hi> were run in among their Flats and Shallows, and there lay grinning and chatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the <hi>Albionians</hi> like so many Monkeys after they have done a Mischief, and know themselves safe. It was reported that the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine by a Private Contract had lent the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:52570:59"/> long before to the Emperour of <hi>Gehenna</hi> to make Serpents and fire-works for joy of the Burning of <hi>Troy-Novant.</hi> However it were the <hi>Palatine</hi> and his two Sorceresses <hi>Medea</hi> and <hi>Circe</hi> bore all the blame. The <hi>Teutonic</hi> Knight Storm'd, the Knight of <hi>Devonia</hi> foam'd, and all the while the <hi>Palatine</hi> made grimaces at both, Which so enrag'd the <hi>Teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonic</hi> Knight, that had it been any other but the Fortune of <hi>England</hi> he had spurn'd him into the Sphear of Saturn, which is the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of all the Seven.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 38.</hi> How the Palatine set the <hi>Albio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and the <hi>Belgians</hi> a third time together by the Ears, by a Wile.</head>
            <p>THe Palatine now thinking he stood upon even terms in point of Honour with his two Rival <hi>Archithalassus</hi>'s, by <hi>Santo Martin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Santo Christophoro,</hi> quo he, I had rather be an absolute Sultan over ten Pagan, than a precarious Monarch over Millions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians. I will have t'other Bout with the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians,</hi> tho' I Sacrifice all the Christians in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion</hi> to the <hi>Manes</hi> of my Great Grandam. It is decreed, nor shall thy Fate, Curst <hi>Albion,</hi> resist my Vow. What tho' she were a <hi>Peterine de Venus,</hi> a <hi>Daughter of Joy,</hi> and blew up
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:52570:59"/> one of her Husbands into a Tree? her Head was Diadem'd, and they ought not to have put her to Death. Now Antichrist assist me, for I have a notable Project in my Head—With that, Sirrah, quo the <hi>Palatine</hi> to a <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> standing by him, the <hi>Belgian</hi> Fleet is out, and Sailing through St. <hi>George</hi>'s <hi>Sleeve,</hi> go forthwith, take an Oyster-boat, and three Men with every one a Snap Cane Gun in their hands; then put up a piece of an old red Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticoat upon the top of the Mast, and Sail through the <hi>Belgian</hi> Fleet; if they refuse to strike to that Rag, let fly at 'em, and denounce War against 'em. To whom the <hi>Triton,</hi> Mighty <hi>Palatine,</hi> quo he, the <hi>Belgians</hi> and we are now at Peace, how shall I answer such a Breach? Slave, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> I am what I am, and will be obey'd. He spoke with such a dreadful Voice, and frown'd so terribly, that the <hi>Triton</hi> seeing the Hair of his Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brows and his Beard almost ready to meet, made such haste, that he broke his Nose against the Door; however he stopt not for that; but ran bleeding down Stairs for fear of a Kick o'the Bum that should have sent him head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>Acheron.</hi> Away he goes with his Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster-boat and his red Rag, and commanded the Belgian <hi>Archithalassus</hi> to strike. At whose Command? quo the Grim <hi>Belgian.</hi> At my
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:52570:60"/> Masters, the Palatine of <hi>Eboracum,</hi> quo the <hi>Albionian Triton.</hi> Be gone, quo the <hi>Belgian,</hi> or else I'le send thee and thy Wherry to the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake. Not strike! quo the <hi>Triton;</hi> and with that he order'd his three <hi>Phocas</hi>'s to snap their three Cane Guns, at the Belgian <hi>Archithalassus.</hi> Upon which, the <hi>Belgian</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd one of his <hi>Phocasses</hi> to let down his Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and give the <hi>Albionian Triton</hi> a Tail-shot; which the <hi>Phocas</hi> plac'd so exactly, and sent it with that fury, that the force of the Wind had almost over-set the <hi>Albionian Fanfan.</hi> With that the <hi>Triton</hi> call'd out with a loud Voice to the Belgian <hi>Archithalassus,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd him in the <hi>Palatine</hi>'s name; and so return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Palatine,</hi> told him what he had done. No more, the War's begun then, quo the <hi>Palatine.</hi> Some relate the Story otherwise, as how that the Palatine commenc'd a Suit upon a <hi>Scan. Mag.</hi> against the <hi>Belgians</hi> by his Attor. Gen. and having got Judgment by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault for Ten hundred thousand Millions of Pounds Damages, he order'd his C. Justiciary to give Sentence against them as Disturbers of the Peace of <hi>Albion,</hi> and Enemies of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. So that there was nothing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but to take the <hi>Belgians</hi> in Execution, which he Swore by the Pavillion of <hi>Mars,</hi> he would do before a Week were over, tho' he
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:52570:60"/> were himself, the <hi>Special Bailiff</hi> And so away he flung to consult his Loyolists what farther course to take.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="39" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 39.</hi> How the Palatine pursu'd his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs against the <hi>Belgians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOw as he was debating which way to get Money to carry on this dismal War, an Envoy came from the King of <hi>Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> to tell him, that the <hi>Belgian</hi> Merchants were coming through <hi>St. Georges Channel,</hi> Laden with all the Riches of the <hi>East,</hi> which if he could but seize, he need never to need a Grand Senate of <hi>Albion</hi> more. Say ye so, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> by the Mass and I'le have it then, tho' it were guarded like the <hi>Hesperian</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard; and so he Summon'd his Council of <hi>Loyolists</hi> together, to consult which way to manage this Affair for the best. Some were for sending away to <hi>Vulcan</hi> immediately to make such a Net as never was seen in the World, all of Massie Iron Wire, and large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to cover all that part of the Ocean from the Island of <hi>Vectis</hi> to the <hi>Astopian</hi> shore; that so the <hi>Belgian</hi> Vessels being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in the Net, the Pagan <hi>Albionians</hi> might seize them as they do Partridge; for that by that means being depriv'd of their
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:52570:61"/> Canvas Wings, they could only flutter about, but never escape the hands of the <hi>Seizers.</hi> Body of <hi>Caesar,</hi> cry'd one of the <hi>Loyolists,</hi> who the Devil shall throw that Net? The <hi>Titans,</hi> quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> huge brawny-arm'd Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters that when they are taking a Nap in the Sun, every one Covers an Acre of Ground with his Body. Nowns, cry'd another, such a Net will be a Hundred years a making. No, no, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> in a Quarter of an hour. I beseech yee, Mighty <hi>Palatine,</hi> crys a third, I think there's a better way than this; to send for the Massie Mountains of <hi>Penmen, Maur</hi> and <hi>Malvern</hi> Hills, and if these will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, fetch the Peek of <hi>Tenariffe,</hi> with the Highlands of <hi>Caledonia,</hi> and sink 'em all in the Narrow Seas, between the <hi>Iccian</hi> Port, in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopia,</hi> and the City of <hi>Durovernum</hi> in <hi>Albion.</hi> Thus shall you stop the <hi>Belgians,</hi> that they shall not be able to go backward nor forward. Besides these vast Excrescencies of the Earth, are but disfigurements to <hi>Albion,</hi> and would do better in the Sea to make a brave Bridge for the King of <hi>Astopia</hi> to come and assist yee against the <hi>Grand Senate.</hi> The <hi>Palatine</hi> lik'd this Project extreamly well; but then quo He, who the Devil shall help us at this dead lift? Morbleu, cry'd one of the <hi>Loyolists,</hi> 'tis a strange thing that there should not be so much
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:52570:61"/> as one grain of Faith among all Us; for then we might remove these Mountains our selves.</p>
            <p>But while they were labouring these great Machinations, in came the terrible Triton <hi>Hamshirothemsol;</hi> to whom, after they had made known their Debates, by the Power of Fortune, quo he, now I think on't, Sir <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> I have a whole Marble Fountain full of <hi>Remora</hi>'s at home i' my Garden, which I keep tame on purpose, for such occasions as these. They are but little Fish 'tis true, not much bigger than <hi>Menows,</hi> but their vertue is such, that by clinging to the sides of a Ship, they will stop a Vessel under Sail, tho' she were as big as a small Island, that she shall not be able to go forward or backward. With these <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora</hi>'s will I stop the <hi>Belgian</hi> Merchants, and when I have once stopt 'em, then let me alone for the rest. As for breaking the League, ne'r trouble your self, Sir <hi>Palatine,</hi> I am never without a Fly-boat full of Liberty of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to serve a Friend.</p>
            <p>The Palatine was right glad to hear this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal of the Triton <hi>Hamshirothemsol,</hi> and suckt it down to his heart as the only Cordial, that could relieve his all so bemir'd Imaginations: he applauded, commended, extoll'd the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Triton,</hi> and told him he would make him
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:52570:62"/>
               <hi>Archithalassus</hi> of <hi>Albion,</hi> if he made him but Master of the <hi>Belgian</hi> Treasures. Away went the terrible <hi>Triton</hi> full of <hi>Belgian</hi>-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding thoughts; and taking along with him a small handful of the <hi>Albionian</hi> Navy lay perdue behind a great Rock just in the Road where the <hi>Belgian</hi> Merchants were to pass; and as soon as they appear'd the terrible Triton sent his <hi>Remora</hi>'s among 'em. 'Tis true, the <hi>Remora</hi>'s put a stop to the <hi>Belgian</hi> Merchants for some time; and then the terrible <hi>Triton</hi> came up with 'em, and commanded 'em to surrender up their Treasure. Not so fast <hi>Tom,</hi> quo They; we did not purchase it so easily. With that the <hi>Terrible Triton</hi> repeated his Commands in the Thundring Language of Broadsides. Which put the <hi>Belgians</hi> into a great Amazement at first, to find their Vessels stopt upon the open Sea; but at length per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving nothing but Violence and Robbery design'd against them by those with whom they suppos'd themselves to have been at Peace, confirm'd by Solemn League and Triple Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, they conferr'd three Minutes with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Nature, and finding by her Laws there was no way but to repel force with force, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd the Justice of their Cause to their Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; and after that, bestirring themselves with a Courage suitable to their Innocency, so
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:52570:62"/> belabour'd the <hi>Terrible Triton,</hi> that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd him to quit his Prey before he could get enough to repair the Dammages of the Engagement. As you shall many times see a number of Crows drive a great Kite from a dead Horse, before he has a quarter satisfy'd his hunger. Which made the <hi>Terrible Triton</hi> curse his ill luck, and Swear that the <hi>Palatine</hi>'s Misfortune haunted him.</p>
            <p>When the Palatine heard this ill News, he was quite down i' the mouth, hung his Lip, and eat up one of his Gloves for madness. Curs'd <hi>Hamshirothemsol,</hi> quo he, had I my self been there, I would have made no more to have swallow'd Seventy two <hi>Belgian</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants than to have devour'd five fresh Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings at a Breakfast. I'le be peel'd like a raw Onyon if this same slave ever pray'd to the Goddess of <hi>Loretto</hi> before he fell on. Fool that I was, had I but sent as many <hi>Saracens,</hi> Heads and all, they would have brought me every one a Ship in their Mouths. Just at this instant in came <hi>Hamshirothemsol</hi> himself, and finding the <hi>Palatine</hi> in such a heat, Sir <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> cry'd he, I defie either you or any man living to have done more than I did—But, Sir, the <hi>Belgians</hi> lin'd all the Sides of their Vessels with raw Eelskins, and so slipt out of my clutches. How! quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> lin'd
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:52570:63"/> the Outsides of their Vessels with raw Eel-skins! Yes, Sir, quo <hi>Hamshirothemsol,</hi> lin'd the sides of their Ves<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>els with raw Eelskins—and your <hi>Remora</hi>'s will never touch Vessels that are so lin'd—and by the Beard of <hi>Pantagruel,</hi> quo the Terrible <hi>Triton,</hi> I'le send him for a New years Gift to the Devil that denies this to be true.—Patience, Noble <hi>Triton,</hi> quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> this was more than I knew—when men speak reason, rational men must believe 'em.—For, as 'tis not improbable, so 'tis probable, and as 'tis probable, 'tis credible; and as 'tis credible, so 'tis not unlikely.—Pork and Pease choak me Sir, quo the <hi>Terrible Triton,</hi> if it be n't as I tell yee, Sir.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="40" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 40.</hi> Of the Great Preparations which the <hi>Palatine</hi> made to Encounter the <hi>Belgians</hi> a Third time.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Palatine</hi> being thus appeas'd, went to the King of <hi>Albion,</hi> and told him he had begun a new War with the <hi>Belgians.</hi> A new War with the <hi>Belgians!</hi> quo the King of <hi>Albion,</hi> how can that be? when I have so lately strook up a new League with the King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> the King of the <hi>Arragonians</hi> and the <hi>Belgians</hi> themselves. When <hi>Jupiter</hi> Swears by <hi>Styx,</hi> he never violates his Oath.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:52570:63"/> No matter for that, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> I have done that already for yee. Shame on all ill luck, quo the King of <hi>Albion,</hi> you will still be medling with Business, and yet were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fit for it. Tell not me, Sir, what I am fit for, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> don't you know there's another Alliance between the King of <hi>Astopia,</hi> and You and Me, which you have seal'd more solemnly than ever <hi>Jupiter</hi> could do by Swearing by <hi>Styx.</hi> If it lye upon your Stomach, drink a little <hi>Lethe,</hi> that's the next River to <hi>Styx,</hi> and that will wash it quite out of your Memory. There's a time for all things, <hi>Palatine,</hi> quo the <hi>Sultan,</hi> there's a time for all things; that's an <hi>Arcanum</hi> not to be disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd as yet. We must do something first to dazle the Eyes of the <hi>Grand Senate.</hi> Don't tell me of the <hi>Grand Senate,</hi> Sir, quo the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> I have begun the War with the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians,</hi> and you must and shall prosecute it. Where's the Money, <hi>Palatine?</hi> quo the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi> Drain the Sea, Sir, quo the <hi>Palatine;</hi> I am told, said he, the bottom of the <hi>Ocean</hi> is much richer than are the Bowels of the Earth. 'Tis but fishing there for Gold, as yee do for Ballast in the River of <hi>Thamesis,</hi> and you may bring up a whole Tun at every cast of your Drag-net. Never was the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Nero</hi> so sure of meeting with Q. <hi>Dido</hi>'s
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:52570:64"/> Treasures that were said to be hidd'n under Ground in <hi>Africa,</hi> as the <hi>Palatine</hi> was assur'd of finding Mountains of Gold at the Bottom of the Sea. Insomuch that he sent for several of the most wealthy Merchants of <hi>Troy-novant,</hi> and told 'em of his design, and the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of it; and at the same time two Loyolists made two long Speeches upon the same subject, and so well convinc'd the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the Reality of the Thing, that they lent the Palatine a Hundred and fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pounds upon the Security of the Project; and others advanc'd large Sums for Patents to set forth so many draining Ships for their own share, allowing such a Profit to the Palatine as <hi>Archithalassus</hi> of <hi>Albion.</hi> Ah marry, Palatine, quo the <hi>Sultan,</hi> I like this way of Draining the Sea well; let 'em have Patents as many as will; I'le sell 'em all the Green Wax i' my Kingdom at this rate. Now if this were true, it was one of the subtilest Contrivances that ever the Palatine was guilty of in his life.</p>
            <p>But this was not all; for he sent to the King of <hi>Astopia,</hi> to let him understand that he was resolv'd to make a general Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against all the Christians in <hi>Albion,</hi> and to put all the Penal Laws and Statutes of the Realm in Execution against them: and offer'd him the Security of the Fines, Mulcts,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:52570:64"/> Estreatments, and Forfeitures of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians for another large Sum of Money to be repaid with Interest; which the King of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopia</hi> accepted. However it were, the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine got Ships from <hi>Astopia,</hi> and Ships in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion,</hi> and what with the one and the other, patch'd up a most formidable Navy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the <hi>Belgians;</hi> of which the Sultan of <hi>Albion</hi> made him a second time <hi>Architha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lassus,</hi> and bid him go on and prosper: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper! quo the <hi>Palatine</hi> to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> my life to a <hi>Gravesend</hi> Toast, we prosper this Bout. For, said he, mark the Course of Fate. The <hi>Phenicians</hi> of <hi>Carthage</hi> tugg'd with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans</hi> in two Salt-water Wars▪ but in the third they were confounded &amp; brought to shame. So the <hi>Belgians</hi> have held it against the <hi>Albionians,</hi> for these two last Wars; but let 'em ware the third.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="41" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 41.</hi> How the Palatine went to seek out the <hi>Belgians,</hi> but found 'em not, and of his Resolutions thereupon.</head>
            <p>THe War being thus declar'd, and the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionians</hi> being joyn'd with the <hi>Astopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the Tritons of both Navies mounted their several Sea-Horses, under the Conduct of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> who was <hi>Archithalassus</hi> of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:52570:65"/>
               <hi>Albion.</hi> These Sea-Horses were the most ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Monsters that ever were seen; for they had every one ten pair of grey Canvas Wings; out of their sides gap'd a number of Mouths that spit Fire, and huge Gobbets of Iron in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of Flegm, as big as Saracen's Heads; upon their Backs. They carry'd huge Towers that would hold, some of 'em a thousand men; and their Bellies were continually stufft with Brew'd Water, Brandy, Salt Pork, and Beef, Gun-Power, Crossbar-shot, and the Devil and all. Their Bridles were fasten'd to their Tails, which were of Wood, and so contriv'd, that with a small Curb, considering the Bulk of the Sea-Horse, you might wind him and turn him, and make him wheel about with the strength of one or two <hi>Phocases,</hi> tho the Sea-Horse were as big as fifty over grown Came's. The <hi>Albionians</hi> and <hi>Astopians</hi> being mounted upon these hugeous Sea Monsters, set forth and flew to the Coasts of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Belgium,</hi> to find out the <hi>Belgians,</hi> who being mounted upon other Sea Monsters of the same nature, but no less terrible, whether out of Fear or Policy kept themselves close and would not be seen. Whereupon the <hi>Palatine</hi> Transported with his wonted Bravery and Courage, Ascending the Steeple of the Tower which his own Sea-Horse carried on his Back
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:52570:65"/> by means of a long Ladder of Ropes, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Stentorian</hi> Trumpet to his Mouth, call'd out to the <hi>Belgians</hi> in a most Terrible and Astonishing Tone, <hi>Hounsfoots, Skellums, Scoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drels,</hi> Bougre diables, <hi>Cowards, Dastards, Lourdants, Lourdens, Marroufles, Butter-boxes,</hi> hoy there—come forth with a vengeance, come out with a Wannion, appear and be pox'd.—Hoy there—d' ye think I ha' nothing else to do but to wait your leisure?—hoy there.—Come out Varlets, Slaves, come out <hi>Canaille</hi> of the World—come and receive your Doom from my Victorious hand—or else Yield, Submit, Surrender and acknowledge that I am the renowned <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Eboracum</hi> that has now twice O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, Vanquish'd, Subdu'd, Beaten and Triumph'd over the White-liver'd, Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zy, Lozelly, <hi>Belgians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Palatine breath'd forth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se defiances with such a Sonorous, Thundring, Amazing, Stupifying utterance, that the very Ocean trembl'd for above twelve Leagues round, and opening her Bowels for fear swallow'd up several Flats and Banks of Sand, which till then well known were never seen after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Belgians</hi> had more wit than to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack a Raging Lyon in his fury, so that they
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:52570:66"/> let the Palatine alone to spend his fury with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out answering a tittle? They would not so much as vouchsafe him a T—in his Teeth, but kept themselves husht and quiet, well knowing the <hi>Palatine</hi> could do 'em no harm, and that oft-times it happen'd according to the Proverb, <hi>Many People Threaten, that come to be well beaten.</hi> Let him vapour quo they, we'l fight when we see occasion. Which the <hi>Palatine</hi> perceiving, came down again as he went up, &amp; calling his <hi>Tritons</hi> about him, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Triton</hi>'s, quo he, the day's our own. We have dar'd 'em to their Teeths, we have braved them to their Noses, and yet the Son's of Fear and Trepidation will not Stir. 'Tis a rule in fighting that if a man be challeng'd and refuses to fight, he's a dastard and owns himself beaten. Were they not afraid of us, they would come out; but they are afraid of us, and therefore they keep in. <hi>Veni, vidi, vici.</hi> 'Tis a plain case—Conquest waits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and triumph attends us—And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so said, he sent away to all the points of the compass to each a particular Herald, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides a dozen Mercuries with winged heels to the City of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> to carry the News of the Great Victory which he had obtain'd over the <hi>Belgians.</hi> Presently the Sea Horses fell a bellowing, the <hi>Triton's</hi> fell a drinking, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:52570:66"/> the <hi>Phocas</hi>'s express'd their joy in Snap-Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons. But when the Tydings arriv'd at <hi>Troy-Novant,</hi> you would have thought the City had been all of a Blaze; Men of fourscore might have read a Doctor of Physick's Bill without Spectacles by the Light of the Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires; The Bells rung, the rabble shouted, and there was such a confusion of noises, that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral new bury'd people started up out of their Coffin's to know what was the matter they could not sleep quietly i' their Graves. But the main thing of all was, that the next day the Nine <hi>Muses</hi> all in White Vestments and their hair dishevell'd, and adorn'd with Garlands of Flowers of various sorts, attended by a Legion of Poets and Rhimers went to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> with whole Cartloads of Panegyricks and Encomiums of the Palatines valour and conduct. In confirmation of which the Seer <hi>Hindus &amp; Pantherus</hi> wrote a large Poem of the reality of <hi>Nonentities</hi> and <hi>Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="42" type="chapter">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:52570:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 42.</hi> Of the great perplexity the Palatine was in.</head>
            <p>BUT notwithstanding all this boasting, Ranting and Triumphing, the <hi>Palatine</hi> was very much perplexed and tormented in mind, for fear lest the <hi>Belgians</hi> should come out after these <hi>Rodomantades,</hi> and thrash him as they did before: Which would have been such a <hi>Hare-lip</hi> in his Reputation tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the <hi>State-surgery</hi> in the World would never be able to sow up again. While he was in this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> he fell a sleep, and as all the ancient <hi>Hero</hi>'s were direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in dreams what to do in a case of necessity, so did the Emperor of <hi>Gehenna</hi> send the Spirit <hi>Oniar</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct his good Friend and Ally the Palatine; Who having dreamt a strange dream, accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved forthwith to put his dream in execution. To this purpose he sent for two Monstrous <hi>Saracens,</hi> which he entertain'd among others for emergent occasions. Monsters indeed, for they were so tall, that they were not above Arm-hole high in the water, wading in the deepest part of the Sea: They had two Eyes in the usual places, and a third in the middle of their foreheads, all as big as whole Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Bullets: and they had six Arms and four Legs apiece, with seven Fingers and seven Toes upon each Hand and Foot: and they had a peculiar Quality, that they could stoop, and walk and breathe under water for five hours together. To these Monstrous <hi>Saracens,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Trusty <hi>Saracens,</hi> quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> go find out the <hi>Belgian</hi> Sea-horses, and bore wide holes in their bellies, that the water may rush in, and sink 'em to the bottom of the Ocean. Spare not one, I charge yee, but serve all alike, and for the reward of your accomplish'd work, expect two Tuns of <hi>Castillian</hi> Gold.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:52570:67"/>
            <p>The <hi>Saracens</hi> thus encourag'd, got thirty vast <hi>Augurs</hi> apiece, ten yards in circumference at the boaring place, which they hung at their backs, and so went wading through the Sea in prosecution of the Palatines dismal design. But the Silver-slipper'd <hi>Thaumantis,</hi> having over-heard the terrible Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions given by the Palatine to the <hi>Saracens,</hi> flew presently to the <hi>Belgians,</hi> and gave them full In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the mischief that was intended against them. The Tidings of this contrivance set all the <hi>Belgians</hi> upon the watch, and as they were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn'd, so they made all the haste imaginable to be fore-arm'd; and they lookt out so sharp, that at length by the heaving of the Sea, and the foaming of the forc'd Waves, they perceiv'd where the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens</hi> were coming along. Presently they threw out their Whale-hooks, and Grapling-Irons fasten'd to the end of great Cables, some of which so lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly stuck in the Ribs of one of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> that they pull'd him up by the help of their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stalls and other massie Engines, roaring and bellowing like all the Bulls of <hi>Basan</hi> in a Herd at once, and so they dragg'd him to the shore, and over-master'd by number, laid him upon the dry Sand, stretched out like <hi>Leviathan</hi> himself, at his full length of threescore yards, and thirty yards in breadth. The first thing they did, they put out his three Eyes with burning firebrands, through the torments of which (for notwithstanding his Bulk, he was but Cow-hearted) they forc'd him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess the whole design, and who set him at work. Which done, they slit the <hi>Continuum</hi> of his Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe, which was Mortar-piece bore, and having flead off his Skin five Inches thick, and cover'd all over with Scales, and pull'd out his heart, as big as a great Oyl-Jarr, they bury'd the <hi>Promethean</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kass
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:52570:68"/> in the Sands. In his heart were discover'd all the marks of Cruelty and Barbarism; for it was hairy, and as hard as <hi>Adamant.</hi> Both the skin and the heart were sold by the <hi>Belgians</hi> to the <hi>Loyolists,</hi> who purchas'd them with a great sum of money, and sent them to New <hi>Babylon,</hi> where they are kept very choicely as the Relicks of a Martyr that suffer'd for the Pagan Cause.</p>
            <p>As for the other <hi>Saracen,</hi> what became of him, no body knows, neither is it a matter of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to make any farther enquiry after him. But this we have to say, that when the Palatine heard the News of this Disaster, and the ill success of his Project, he lay roaring three days and nights together, like the King of <hi>Palestine</hi> for the loss of his Child, and would neither eat nor drink in all that time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="43" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 43.</hi> Of something worth your Hearing.</head>
            <p>NOW when the <hi>Palatine</hi> had thus miscarri'd in a Barbarous and unprincely Project, which he thought could never have fail'd, he whistled all his Sea-horses together, and returning back to the Coast of <hi>Albion,</hi> he shut them up in a wide Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, or Gulph of the Sea, call'd the Gulph of <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuso,</hi> and barricado'd 'em up with an invisible Chain of daring boldness to vain-glorious presumption, a mile in circumference, and thirty Leagues in length, which reach'd from one end of the Bay to the other. Now having, as he thought, thus secur'd all his Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horses from all assaults of the <hi>Belgians,</hi> he went himself ashore, attended by the greatest number of his <hi>Tritons.</hi> For you must know, that after the ill success of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> the Palatine had conceiv'd another design in his head, and by the terrible pains
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:52570:68"/> which he felt in his scull, he was of opinion that his time of Delivery was by. To supply therefore the want of <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Midwife, (for there was not one among all his <hi>Tritons</hi> or <hi>Phocas</hi>'s that knew how to cleave a scull, and close it together again) the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> sent for a Son of <hi>Esculapius</hi> to open his scull with a Trepan: Who had no sooner made a hole on both sides the <hi>Coronal Suture</hi> about the breadth of an <hi>Astopian</hi> Crown piece, (which the Artist was above two hours a-doing, for the Palatines scull was very hard and thick) but out leap'd an Embrio of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in the nature of a Bears Cub, without form or shape; which the <hi>Palatine</hi> therefore undertook to lick into Lineaments. But when he had lickt it, till his Tongue was almost as dry as the out-side of a <hi>Westphalie-Ham,</hi> he could never lick it to such a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but that it still retain'd a hideous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strosity. For as the Annals of those times report, it was to have delv'd under the Sea till he came to the Shore of the lower <hi>Belgium,</hi> and so to have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermin'd all the Country as far as <hi>Ultrajectum</hi> one way, to the strong Town of <hi>Obtricum</hi> another way, in order to the blowing up of all the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated <hi>Belgium,</hi> Towns, Cities, Families, Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Virgins, Children, Cattel and all. To this purpose he sent for <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and made him his chief Engineer and Overseer of his Works, who brought along with him a Legion of <hi>Peruvian</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners accustom'd to delve under the Earth, in search of the great God of the World <hi>Aurum.</hi> To which, the <hi>Palatine</hi> having joyn'd his own <hi>Phocas</hi>'s, they had proceeded so far, that in ten days they were got within forty Fathom of the Foundations of the Northern Hemisphere.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="44" type="chapter">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:52570:69"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 44.</hi> How the <hi>Palatine</hi> was surpriz'd by the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians,</hi> and how be sacrific'd his Vice-Archithalassus, the Knight of the Pointed Mount to his Despair.</head>
            <p>BUT while the <hi>Palatine</hi> was thus busily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, and lay with all his Sea-horses, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridl'd, unsaddl'd, at rack and manger, secure and careless of any thing else, but of carrying on the Great work which he had begun, the <hi>Belgians</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving some inkling of his design, and being inform'd by their Scouts in what Posture the Palatine lay, and how the <hi>Tritons</hi> were all ashore, some caressing their fair <hi>Clytemnestra</hi>'s, others carousing the Confusion of the Christians, and lambasting the unexpected <hi>Belgians</hi> in their Cups, the sedulous and wary <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians</hi> resolv'd to lay hold of the opportunity. To which purpose they nointed the hoofs of all their Sea-horses, with equal parts of the Oils of <hi>Silentium</hi> and <hi>Celeritas,</hi> and so setting forth betimes in the morning, by the means of a large Curtain which the Silver-slipper'd <hi>Iris</hi> drew before them, made of the same stuff as her own Garments; only that it was not of so many colours, nor embroder'd with the Sun-beams, they fell undiscover'd upon the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionians,</hi> before they perceiv'd that any Enemy was near them. And it is verily thought that the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians</hi> had then destroy'd all the <hi>Albionian</hi> Sea-horses, but for the terrible resistance which some few of the <hi>Albionian Tritons</hi> made, that lay without the Entrance into the Gulph, as Out-guards to the rest. Presently the <hi>Sea-horses</hi> fell a roaring and bellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and spouting fire at one another, as if so many <hi>Bellerophon</hi>'s had been fighting so many <hi>Chimaera</hi>'s, which were Monsters that breathed nothing but fire, and would undo a hundred rich Farmers in the twinckling of an Eye, by destroying all their stocks
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:52570:69"/> upon the ground. Immediately the rest of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> took the Alarm, and sent to the <hi>Palatine</hi> to know what they should do; but he was so deeply engag'd in the Military game of <hi>Draughts,</hi> with the chiefest of his Minions, <hi>Misodemus, Patraloias, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrannus, Cacaflexipolis, Cacodaemon, Ocnos, Hamotes,</hi> and several others of the same gang, that he made them little or no answer. For he was so wrapt up with assurance of the success of his new Project to destroy the <hi>Belgians,</hi> by blowing up their Country, that he lookt upon himself as already Lord of the Earth; and as for his own <hi>Albionians,</hi> he as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally hated them as the <hi>Belgians.</hi> But being press'd by Messengers upon Messengers that were sent to him to hasten Relief, Bold Slaves, quo the <hi>Palatine,</hi> what means this sawcy Intrusion upon my Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? How many <hi>Tritons</hi> are there that make oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition? Not above six or seven, quo the Messengers. Enow in all Conscience, reply'd the <hi>Palatine,</hi> with a surly frown, to fight the cowardly <hi>Belgians.</hi> Were I there my self, I'd beat the Scoundrils with half the number. But when I challeng'd them, they would not come out to me; and now they are come to me, I scorn to go out to them.</p>
            <p>Spoke like your self, far dreaded <hi>Palatine,</hi> cry'd one of his <hi>Hibernian Argonauts,</hi> by name <hi>Pampone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros;</hi> and at the same time lifting to his Nose a whole <hi>Punch-bowl</hi> of Lotos-berry Brandy, began a health to the Perdition of the <hi>Belgians;</hi> which the <hi>Palatine</hi> pledging, fell into such a soporiferous <hi>Trance,</hi> that he became altogether insensible of the great Trust which the <hi>Albionians</hi> had repos'd in him. For such is the nature of the <hi>Lotos</hi> fruit, that whoever drinks the Liquor where it is infus'd, presently for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets his Native Country. Others say, that he was enchanted by the terrible Necromancer <hi>Prodotes,</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:52570:70"/> who had a great <hi>Ascendant</hi> over the Palatine in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, but where the <hi>Astopian</hi> King was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, and being moreover a desperate Enemy of the <hi>Albionians,</hi> he so contriv'd it with the great Wind-broaker <hi>Eolus,</hi> that there was no Wind to be had for love or money to favour the <hi>Albionians;</hi> so that such <hi>Tritons</hi> as were willing to help their fellows, could not: And as for the <hi>Astopians,</hi> they lay by with their Sails furl'd, their <hi>Archithalassus</hi> declaring that he had strict command from his Universal Monarch not to hazard the least Rib of any of the Sea-Monsters under his Conduct, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leave of the <hi>Demons</hi> and Goddesses to whom they were particularly consecrated; for then 'twas to be expected, the Semideities would take care of their own Goods; otherwise it would be unfafe for the <hi>Astopian</hi> Monarch to venture at his own peril against the Will of unconsulted Heaven. Besides tho' 'twere the Custom in <hi>Astopia</hi> for the Seconds as well as the Principals, to fight by Land, yet by Sea the <hi>Astopians</hi> never fought as Seconds, but only lookt on at a distance out of harms way: their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness being only to make a show, and to learn by other mens harms to be wary themselves.</p>
            <p>All this while, tho' the Sea-Monsters on both-sides roar'd, bellow'd and disgorg'd Fire and Flames at one another like the furnaces of <hi>Aetna,</hi> the Palatine sat no more concerned or in any martial passion, than if the <hi>Tritons</hi> had been only pelting each other with <hi>Pruen-Stones,</hi> till <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> coming to him with all his Crew at his Heels, and telling him he had sapp'd three Leagues under the Sea, but could go no farther, in regard he had met with the Massy impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable Adamantine Rock to which the Poles of the World were fasten'd, which put the <hi>Palatine</hi> into such a Rage, that he flung a full Punch-bowl of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:52570:70"/> Brandy-wine at <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog's</hi> Head, and curs'd <hi>Belzebub</hi> for putting him upon the best Project in the World, and leaving him in the lurch: Nor would any thing atone his fury, till word was brought him, that the Vice-<hi>Archithalassus,</hi> otherwise call'd the Knight of the <hi>pointed Mountain</hi> was drowned, for want of timely aid, in the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and that the <hi>Princely Jacomo,</hi> one of the best Sea-Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters the Albionians had, after <hi>she</hi> had laid about her like an Host of <hi>Amazons,</hi> and with her brazen Heels and Iron jaws had kickt two <hi>Belgian Incendiary Towers,</hi> to the bottom of the Sea, and had rent and torn and mangl'd several others of the <hi>Belgian Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gasits's,</hi> that they were no longer able to endure the rowling of the Waves, was at length for want of due Succor sacrificed to <hi>Neptune,</hi> by a daring <hi>Belgian</hi> Incendiary; and that several others of the bravest and stoutest of the <hi>Albionian Tritons</hi> were devoured by the <hi>Belgian</hi> Sea-Monsters; as being overpowr'd by number, and choosing rather to sacrifice their Lives to the Honour of their Country, and to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in after ages the Monuments of their deserted Valour, than to surrendur themselves a Prey to their Insulting Enemies.</p>
            <p>At this the <hi>Palatine,</hi> while the <hi>Necromancer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes</hi> stood snickering at his Elbow, began to rowse himself; and are they gone? quoth he; is the <hi>Knight</hi> of the <hi>pointed Mountain</hi> suffocated in the Briny Ocean? And are so many of my <hi>Tritons</hi> devoured by the <hi>Belgian</hi> Sea-Monsters? Let 'em go—what said our Royal <hi>Beaupere,</hi> of blessed memory; I trust I have within my Realm five hundred as good as they—When the ancient Gods were anger'd by the Disgraces and Affronts of Inferiour Mortals it was usual to atone their Indignation by sacrifices the most acceptable: And some would not be co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:52570:71"/> without Humane Victims: Witness <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> a Damsel worth a hundred <hi>Tritons</hi> such as I have lost; yet <hi>Agamemnon</hi> would have her dragg'd to the Altar. And am not I as great as <hi>Agamemnon?</hi> Poor creatures! they fought blindfold, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the mysterious depth of my design in this same <hi>Belgian</hi> War, to waste the wealth and valour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Rebellious <hi>Albionians.</hi> The curse of Antichrist light upon the lazy <hi>Gog and Magog</hi> for stopping thus at an Adamantin Rock. Had I been in his room, and furnish'd with his brawny Arms, I would have delv'd up the foundations of the Earth, to have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermin'd all <hi>Belgium.</hi> And now my honour'd <hi>Argo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauts,</hi> to shew what I can do; I'le make the best of what has happen'd in spite of all the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="45" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 45.</hi> How the Palatine wrested the Victory out of the <hi>Belgians</hi> hands, and of the Great Bon-fire he made for joy.</head>
            <p>THus spoke the Palatine, and having so said, he sent to enquire what was become of the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians?</hi> To which it was answered that they were gone away with Victory and the honour of the day. Are they gone quo the Palatine, by the Testicles of <hi>Pegasus</hi> I'le after 'em. With that he order'd the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancer Prodotes</hi> to untye his bag, and let loose all the favourable Fluster-blusterers &amp; presently muste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all his Sea-Horses together, except such as were so terribly wounded and disabled that they could not stir, immediately pursu'd the <hi>Belgian's</hi> with Wings display'd, and all the <hi>Titans</hi> with every one a pair of Massy-bellows blowing Wind in the Tails of his Sea-horses. But as their good fortune would have it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Palatine</hi> could get to the Coasts of <hi>Belgium,</hi> the <hi>Belgian's</hi> dreading the fury of his pursuit, had lockt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:52570:81"/> themselves into their <hi>Sea-Fortresses,</hi> where they were as safe as Gold in a Misers Chest, with their Masts stuck with Lawrel, and Crown'd with Garlands of all sorts of Flowers. This the Palatine lik'd right well; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the more he was assur'd of the Resolution of the <hi>Belgians</hi> not to stir, the more eager he seem'd to be at 'em. Sometimes he was for <hi>Gogg</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> and his crews removing the Shelves and Flats; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he was for their carrying the Sea-horses upon their Shoulders over the Sands; but these Projects not being approv'd he drew up all his Sea-Horses in the form of a half Moon, set his Sea-Monsters a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and buried no less than five hundred thousand pound Jewish Shekels of round Iron Balls in the Sands, as if he had intended to cram the Metal again into the Bowels of the Earth from whence it was first taken, Shouting and Bouncing continually for four Days and Nights together. Which done, look ye, quo he, we have besieg'd 'em thus long in their own Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, and you see they dare not come out: Now then, will the World believe them to be Victors that dare not fight the Vanquish'd? I am not bound to wait upon their tai's till doomsday. With that he gave Order that the whole Fleet of Sea Monsters should open three times▪ set all his Sea-Musick a playing, Trumpets, Clarions, Flutes, Hautbois, Drums and Kettle-Drums, and so as if he had been gainer of the great Battel of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> returned in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to the place from whence he came.</p>
            <p>He was no sooner come back, but he dispatch'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Fame before with a whole sack full of relations, as much as she could well carry, to <hi>Alba Regalis:</hi> Where she had no sooner emptied her fardel, but all the City of <hi>Troy-Novant</hi> was full of the joyful tydings of the greatest Victory that ever was obtain'd over the <hi>Belgians.</hi> For confirmation of which several e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:52570:82"/>
               <hi>Tritons,</hi> by the Palatines Order, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her close at the Heels, with the particulars of so many <hi>Belgian</hi> Centaurs slain, so many desperately, so many mortally, so many slightly wounded. So many Sea-Monsters destroy'd, so many taken, so many disabled; So many thousand <hi>Phocas</hi>'s Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, so many slain. To which they added such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable circumstances as would have made a <hi>Turk</hi> believe 'em: As how that the Number of the slain <hi>Belgians</hi> had invited all the smell-feast Whales out of the North Seas, to the great disappointment of the Merchants in Whale-bones and Train Oyl; that there had been more Gold rings taken by the Mackarel men upon gutting their Fish, than <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> sent to <hi>Cartha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> after the Slaughter of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Romans at <hi>Cannae.</hi> In all the Coffee-houses, there were some that made it their business to sit at the upper end of the Tables, and Swear to the truth of all this, and nam'd the very place where the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, to the Leewards of the Islands of <hi>Meda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothi</hi> and <hi>Rovack,</hi> says one. No, says another, 'twas within three Leagues of the Islands of <hi>Tohu Vavohu,</hi> which while one denied and the other affirm'd, there was such thumping upon the Tables with clinch'd fists, that there were almost as many <hi>Nicotia-Fistu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la's</hi> broken in the Land contest, as there were <hi>Belgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> kill'd in the Sea engagement. But nothing gave so much reputation to this Chimerical Victory as the double diligence of monsieur <hi>Gazet,</hi> a most ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequious observer of the Palatines Command, and one that always at that time spoke the Language of the Court; who left no stone unturn'd to conveigh the blessed news to all the parts and corners of <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> Horse Posts, and Foot Posts, Expresses and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers, your clouted Shoon Mercuries, and Winged Charioters; Nay there was not a wind in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:52570:82"/> but what had a Pacquet of Advice ty'd to his tail to convey the more speedily these joyful tydings to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very cranny of the Nation; Which by way of reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation returned as well loaden with addresses to the Palatine, full of adulation and rapture, Exultations and rejoycings for his Success, for the preservation of his Person, as if he had been the only <hi>Palladium</hi> upon which the welfare of the Kingdom depended.</p>
            <p>But when it was rumor'd that the <hi>Palatine</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to <hi>Alba-Regalis,</hi> multitudes pour'd forth to meet him; some in Gondola's, some in Brigandines, some in Gallyfoists, &amp; <hi>Triremes,</hi> after the Old Roman manner, believing that he would have made his Entry into the River <hi>Thamesis</hi> in a Sea-Chariot, drawn by Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins, and attended by <hi>Neptune,</hi> with all the Nere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ides dancing about him, but being deceived in their Expectations; some swore they never mistrusted the Truth of the Heathen Poetry till then: for that had there been any such things as <hi>Marine</hi> Dieties, <hi>Sea-Nymphs,</hi> and <hi>Mermaids,</hi> they could not have fail'd of their duties upon such an occasion as that. But others answered, that the Palatine had so frighted them with the noise of his victorious Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they lay quaking and trembling all at the bottom of the Sea, and durst not make their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance before the <hi>Terrour</hi> of the <hi>Ocean:</hi> and that the Palatine was such, there could be no greater proof than that <hi>Neptune</hi> himself had Abdicated his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions for fear of him. However, other Honours were done him by his Vassals the Antichristians. For presently came the <hi>Loyolists, Mateologians, Maenades,</hi> and <hi>Tirelupins,</hi> and consecrated all the River of <hi>Thamesis</hi> from the <hi>Esperanza</hi> to <hi>Alba-Regalis,</hi> and turn'd it into <hi>Gringorian</hi> water, which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fum'd all the way, with all the rich-scented Gumms of <hi>Arabia Foelix,</hi> and strew'd it with Ivy, Lawrel,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:52570:83"/> Myrtles, Poppies, Daffadowndillies, Roses, and all those other Plants and Flowers which were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sacred to Heathen Gods. And thus the Palatine was row'd up a sort of Liquid Elysian Fields, till he came to <hi>Alba-Regalis,</hi> where he was embrac'd, hugg'd and kiss'd by the Sultan of <hi>Albion,</hi> as if he had won him all the Monarchy of <hi>Darius.</hi> But when the Hair-brain'd People came to express their joy in Bonfires, there was not Wood enough to be found in all <hi>Troynovant.</hi> Of which the Palatine being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, he fell into a wonderful Passion, which <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurgus,</hi> one of the <hi>Palatines</hi> Chief Counsellors ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving, Most Noble <hi>Palatine,</hi> quo He, I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd on the other side of the <hi>Thamesis,</hi> contiguous to the Bridge that joyns the two Continents of the <hi>Trinobantines</hi> and the <hi>Canutians,</hi> a huge <hi>Chaos</hi> of wild, rotten, woodden Buildings, fit for nothing but to feed the hungry flames: Give me a wink and I'll undertake to make you one of the greatest Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires that ever dazl'd the Skie, excepting that of <hi>Troynovant</hi> it self, or that which <hi>Phaeton</hi> made for joy of having couzen'd his Father of the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Universe. <hi>Panurgus,</hi> quo the Palatine, I am secure in thy Affection, take thy course. Upon which <hi>Panurgus</hi> calling out his Incendiaries, set all <hi>Austraergon</hi> in such a flame, that the Conflagration lasted for several days and nights together; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly visible to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> but proclaiming the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessful Grandeur of the Palatine to all the surround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Provinces of <hi>Albion.</hi> Great and glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement, quo <hi>Panurgus,</hi> merit the most glorious demonstrations of our joy; and now I think I have out-done the Low Enterprize of the Hebrew Heroe, in setting fire to a little dry Straw in a hot Country.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="46" type="chapter">
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:52570:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 46.</hi> Of the Noise which the Palatines great At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements made in the far distant Regions of the world, and the various Effects of it.</head>
            <p>BY the Light and Blaze of this great Bonfire, Fame flew through all the world from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to Region as swift as Wildfire, which is fifteen hundred Leagues in half an hour. She made a short stop in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> at <hi>Prester John</hi>'s Country, where she told a long story to Queen <hi>Candaces,</hi> and thence fetching a Tour about the Southern Hemisphere, came to the Great Moguls Court, and then pass'd on to the Emperour of <hi>China,</hi> so to the Tartars, and the lately discover'd Common-wealth of <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> in her return homeward taking <hi>Persia, Mingrelia</hi> and <hi>Russia</hi> in her way. It is not to be credited how those far distant Monarchs were astonish'd, and what a Pannick dread seiz'd upon their spirits to hear of the wonderful Atchievements perform'd by the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, while every one thought him in the bowels of his Dominions already. The great <hi>Mogull,</hi> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd and terrifi'd by the Fate of his Predecessor <hi>Porus,</hi> dreaded the coming of another <hi>Alexander,</hi> and looking upon his vast Empire as already lost, tho' of a black, sun-burnt complexion, turn'd as white and as pale as a piece of new fine Holland. The Emperour of <hi>China</hi> had newly drank his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings-draught, and breakfasted just as the news came, at what time the apprehension of the danger he was in, cast him into such a cold sweat, that he brought up all again. And as for the great <hi>Can</hi> of <hi>Tartary,</hi> he was in such a lamentable pickle, that you might have smelt him above ten German Leagues.</p>
            <p>But as for the Female Sex, the Physick of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine's glorious Actions wrought quite after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:52570:72"/> manner: For as there is nothing works so much upon the Minds and Fancies of the High-born Women as Valour, and the Honour of having some renowned Champion fetter'd in the Chains of their Golden Curls, <hi>Candace</hi> found her self so smitten with the charms of the <hi>Palatines</hi> Renown, that burning Love had almost consum'd her bowels, so that she lost the use of her Teeth for six months together. At length she prevail'd with her next neighbour the Great Emperour of <hi>Morocco,</hi> to send a splendid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassie to the Palatine, with offer of all her large Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, if he would but vouchsafe to accept of her and them together, promising withal to admit the Loyolists into her Country, tho' mortally hated by her Subjects, if he would but condescend to her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals. The <hi>Palatine</hi> receiv'd the Embassadors with all the demonstrations of Civility imaginable, and with all the expressions of a Courtier acknowledged the Honour which the Queen of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> had done him; but told them withal, that his business lay at this end of the world, to root out a Northern He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie▪ which he fear'd would cost him the whole time of his life to accomplish. With which Answer the Embassadors returning, the disconsolate <hi>Condace</hi> threw her self into a huge Funeral Pile, and ended her days like <hi>Queen Dido.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next that was ready to hang her self in her own Garters, was the Sister of the Mighty <hi>Aurang Zeeb;</hi> and she lay night and day at her Brother, that she might be chain'd to a Rock like <hi>Andromeda,</hi> and expos'd to the fury of some Sea-Monster: For surely then, thought she, this valorous Champion will flie to my Rescue, and then I shall have an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to tell him my mind. With that she sent him a Diamond as big as an Elephants Head, and a Letter in the Indian Character. But by what mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:52570:72"/> is not known, the Diamond miscarried, and as for the Letter, 'twas Heathen Greek to the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, for he could not read a word in it; so that if the Princess's Brother were so fond as to humour her, 'tis impossible but that she must have paid for her longing, long before this.</p>
            <p>The Princess of <hi>China</hi> was more politick; for she despairing that the Palatine, being so great a Prince as he was, would travel to <hi>China</hi> for a Wife, thought it her duty rather to attend upon him her self: So she got leave of the <hi>Sun</hi> to ride in his Coach-box, and came to <hi>Albion incognito:</hi> But when <hi>Phaeton</hi> had set her down in the West of <hi>Albion,</hi> near the <hi>Mount</hi> of the <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> she heard the doleful news that the Palatine was marry'd above two months before; and how she got back again, there's no body ever could tell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="47" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 47.</hi> How the Palatine marry'd the most Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Messalina</hi> Princess of <hi>Demonia</hi> upon the River <hi>Eridanus,</hi> with whom he had a Golden Mountain, and <hi>Phaetons</hi> Reliques for her Portion.</head>
            <p>IN the midst of all these design'd Addresses of the greatest Princesses in the world, the <hi>Palatine</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving refus'd the Courtship and Caresses of the One, and the rest not rightly understanding which way to make their Addresses, the Princess of <hi>Demonia</hi> got start of them all: for having the Advantage of send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Palatine</hi> her Picture, she so inflam'd him with the sight of her Divine Beauty, that had any of the Pagan Goddesses, <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the blessed <hi>Cecilia,</hi> or the Queen of Heavens Maid of Honour Madam <hi>Agatha,</hi> made love to him in a dream from Heaven, he would not have exchang'd the Carnal Embraces of the Princess <hi>Messalina</hi> for their Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stial
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:52570:73"/> Caresses. Besides that, she was nearly alli'd to the Holy Pontiff of Spiritual <hi>Babylon▪</hi> to whom the <hi>Palatine</hi> was endeared by many ties of Religion, and other Sacred Obligations of Duty and Affection. She was as black as a Raven's wing, yet fair as the Wife of <hi>Menelaus:</hi> Her Breasts were like the Pillars of <hi>Jupiter:</hi> Her Cherry Lips dropt nothing but Manna of <hi>Campania,</hi> and her Breath more odorife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than Balm of <hi>Gilead:</hi> Her Nose was like the <hi>Pharos</hi> of <hi>Egypt:</hi> Her Belly like <hi>Adonis</hi>'s Bed of Roses, and her Thighs like the Pillars of the Gates, of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> keeps the Keys. As she past through <hi>Astopia,</hi> the great Monarch of that Empire, in defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Palatine met her; and beholding her Angelick Perfections, wisht himself the High Priest of <hi>Calecutt,</hi> who by the Religion of that Country has the priviledge to be the King's Taster.</p>
            <p>At the same time, as a Testimonial of the strict and indelible Amity that was between the <hi>Palatine</hi> himself, and to demonstrate what a high value and veneration he had for her incomparable Vertue and Beauty, surpassing (in his Fancy) the <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite</hi> so loudly ex-tolled by the King of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> he presented her with a Mountain all of massy Gold, which had been presented to his great Grandfather <hi>Grangousier,</hi> by the <hi>Iberian</hi> King, a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Mile in circumference, and an <hi>Albion</hi> League high, carry'd by ten thousand <hi>Chrim Tartars,</hi> fifteen foot tall, not missing a quarter of an Inch one of another. Which Mountain serv'd her instead of a Canopy, to keep not only her, but her Chariot from the Rain as she travelled upon the Road. Which Mountain the <hi>Tartars</hi> carry'd upon Pillars of Wood, like a Lord Mayor's Pageant, to the Sea: But there being no Ships big enough to transport it, they made a Portentous <hi>Arbalista</hi> in imitation of the old Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:52570:85"/> Engine, with which they were wont to sling prodigious Stones into besieged Cities, and of which the great <hi>Ptolomy Poliorketes</hi> was the Inventor; by the help of which Engine the <hi>Tartars</hi> first slung the Mountain cross the Ocean from <hi>Astopia</hi> into <hi>Albion,</hi> and then slung themselves after it. And so taking it up again in <hi>Albion,</hi> carry'd it to <hi>Troynovant,</hi> where the <hi>Palatine</hi> melted it down and coyn'd it into mony to defray the Expences of the Famous <hi>Opera</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiline's Conspiracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as she had all these Perfections to recommend her outward form, the Endowments of her Mind were much more amiable; for sweetness of dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition surpassing <hi>Inno;</hi> for Chastity, far excelling the Mother of the Gods, only that she had one fault, that now and then she would take up a Stone with her Ear. For haughty Pride of Mind, she went far beyond <hi>Niobe:</hi> And she had one peculiar faculty, that she could as well have hatch'd Children, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> do Chickens in an Oven, as bear 'em in her Womb.</p>
            <p>No wonder then, that the <hi>Palatine,</hi> ravish'd with all these advantages both of her Body and Soul, sought her by his Embassadors and Proxies with all the diligence and fedulity imaginable, and ventur'd all his future happiness both in this and the world to come, to obtain so inestimable a Jewel. He spar'd for no cost, but presented her with all the Rarities that the Earth could afford, or his Treasury pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase. Among the rest, he sent her an old Smock, old in years, but which the Queen of Heaven, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Di Loretto,</hi> had never worn but once in her life; the <hi>Sudarium,</hi> with the Picture of her Son, taken from the Life in sweat, and the Box of Ointment which <hi>Venus</hi> gave <hi>Phaon</hi> the Ferry-man, who trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported her from <hi>Sicily</hi> into <hi>Italy;</hi> for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:52570:74"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:52570:74"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:52570:75"/> of her Beauty; which so won her heart, that she could not deny him.</p>
            <p>When she arriv'd in <hi>Albion,</hi> he met her with a glorious train of all the <hi>Marine Deities,</hi> both Male and Female, and as a new mark of the great vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration he had for her, recommended to her <hi>Peleus</hi> for her Gentleman Usher, and <hi>Thetis</hi> to be the Mother of her Maids.</p>
            <p>At the Ceremony of the Marriage, the <hi>Pontiff</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> gave her by his Proxy <hi>Panurgus,</hi> the great Emperor of <hi>Dinblonia</hi> held up her Train, and <hi>Alecto</hi> and <hi>Tisiphone</hi> were her two Bride-Maids.</p>
            <p>Her Gown was made all of small Rings of Gold, the void spaces of which were fill'd up with Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds and Rubies; the workmanship of an <hi>Hebrew</hi> lineally descended from the famous Artist that made the Covering of the Jewish Ark.</p>
            <p>The Sheets that she lay in the first night, were of the purest Calicutt that <hi>Oriental India</hi> afforded, printed on both sides with Epithalamiums, Motto's and Ciphers, sent her from the two Luminaries of <hi>Albion, Oxenfordia,</hi> and <hi>Cantabrigia,</hi> and procur'd by the care and industry of the Seer <hi>Obadiah Walkero.</hi> And the Curtains of her Bed were embroider'd with the <hi>Lutetian Massacre,</hi> and the Amours of <hi>Alexander</hi> the VIIth. and <hi>Donna Olympia,</hi> by the Great great Grand-daughter of the Great great Grand-daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Daughters Daughter of <hi>Dorcas</hi> that made Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Coats in the Infancy of the Primitive Church. The Palatine admir'd, worship'd, ador'd her, and three times a week laid his neck at her feet for her to trample upon, with this Motto, <hi>Super Aspidem,</hi> &amp;c. Such was the high esteem and reverence which he had for her: for knowing his defect one way, he suppli'd it in a respect and obedience. But in regard we shall have farther occasion to mention this great
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:52570:75"/> Mistress of the great Master of this Northern part of the world, we shall say no more of her at present.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="48" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>Chap. 48.</hi> How the Palatine, the more to ingratiate himself with his new marry'd Princess, rais'd the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Band of the <hi>Oriflambs</hi> of <hi>Troynovant,</hi> and how he encountred and overthrew the whole Army of the <hi>Chinabeefians, Costardi,</hi> and <hi>Vensonpastig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians,</hi> three great Nations in perpetual Enmity with the Albionians, upon the Plains of <hi>Drappers-hallia.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Palatine</hi> was so overjoy'd with his Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Gold, and so ravish'd with the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Accomplishments of the Princess of <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> that he made it his study to rivet himself into her favour and affection, and sought all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to continue the high opinion she had of his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Conduct, and of his being one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Champions in the World. Nor was it long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Fortune, whose Darling and Minion he was, presented him with one for a New-years Gift. For the <hi>Chinabeefians,</hi> the <hi>Costardi,</hi> and the <hi>Vensonpastiggians,</hi> a wild and savage sort of People, with whom the <hi>Albionians</hi> had been at continual Wars for some hundreds of years, but could never so subdue them, but that they recruited again in spite of their teeths, being still assisted by the <hi>Crembollians</hi> and <hi>Henegghi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> believing that now was their time to recover their Liberty, if they could but strike a Terrour into the <hi>Albionians</hi> by overcoming the Palatine upon whom the <hi>Albionians</hi> depended, as the Antient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines did upon their Champions of <hi>Gath,</hi> sent to the Palatine, more fool-hardy than prudent, as they were, to meet 'em fairly in the Plains of <hi>Drapers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallia,</hi> there to determine the feud which had been so long between them and the <hi>Albionians.</hi> Now the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:52570:76"/> Palatine deeming it but rational to consider the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of these three Nations before he took the field, found that the <hi>Chinabeefians</hi> were a barbarous sort of People, that when they were worsted, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently retreated behind the most formidable <hi>Pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sado</hi>'s imaginable, which they made of the bones of the Sacrifices which they offer'd to their great Idol <hi>Gaster;</hi> from whence it was impossible to force them without a long Siege, and great loss of Men. That the <hi>Vensonpastiggians,</hi> upon a Rout, hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves under spacious Caves, contriv'd with great Art, and cover'd over with a Cement made of the dust of the fruit of the Herb <hi>Triticum,</hi> mixt with Eggs and a certain Unguent which the Antients call'd <hi>Butyrum,</hi> which render'd those Fortifications as strong as the Walls of <hi>Coventria,</hi> which no Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks nor Pickaxes could enter, till they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermin'd and blown up with <hi>Stygian</hi> Gunpowder. And then for the <hi>Custardi,</hi> they were like the wild <hi>Hibernians;</hi> if they were vanquisht, they retir'd into their Boggs, so that there was no way to destroy 'em, but by devouring them and their Walls, and swallowing <hi>Boggs</hi> and all.</p>
            <p>The Palatine having well consider'd all these things, caus'd great Levies of Pioneers to be made amongst the <hi>Bonstomachians</hi> and the <hi>Gasterians,</hi> and order'd them to be extraordinarily furnish'd with all the Utensils and Instruments for Mining and Sapping, as Spades, Shovels, Pickaxes, Mattocks, and long Spoons, such as <hi>Magog</hi> was wont to use when he eat with the Devil.</p>
            <p>More especially he order'd them to furnish themselves with short broad Knives, with Bucks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn Handles, for the more faster holding, to cut their way through all opposition.</p>
            <p>Which done he rais'd the whole Force of the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:52570:76"/>
               <hi>Tyrian-Fetherians,</hi> all approved Champions, and well exercis'd in Arms; and now both Armies being met in the spacious Plains of <hi>Drappershallia,</hi> the <hi>China<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beefians, Vensonpastiggians</hi> and <hi>Costardi</hi> drew up in three Bodies. The <hi>Chinabeefians</hi> had the Vanguard, the <hi>Vensonpastiggians</hi> the Main Battel, and the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stardi</hi> the Rearguard. The <hi>Tyrian-Fetherians</hi> on the other side being rang'd by the <hi>Palatine,</hi> with all the skill and forefight of a prudent Captain. The Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine made them a short Harangue, wherein he gave them to understand, <q rend="margQuotes">That they were not now to fight for their Religion, their Estates, and their Wives and Children, but for what was dearer than all these, their own most precious Lives. For what signified Religion, Estates, Wives &amp; Children, if they had not life to enjoy them? And therefore he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought them for his own and their Honour, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themselves with a Courage equal to that of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> and by the success of that day, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the high opinion which all the world had of their Valour.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Palatine having thus said, in short, the Battel began with an unparallel'd heat and fury, by reason of the stout Resistance which the <hi>Chinabeefians</hi> for a long time made; insomuch that Victory hover'd over the Palatine with a pale and dubious Aspect, till at length, by the undaunted Bravery of the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian-Fetherians</hi> the <hi>Chinabeefians</hi> were forc'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Palisadoe's: at what time the Reserve of <hi>Footbuoyonians</hi> coming in made such an universal havock of all the Enemies Vanguard, that there was not so much as one <hi>Chinabeefian</hi> left to carry the tydings of this dismal loss to their Wives and Children.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vensonpastiggians</hi> held out for some longer time, but the <hi>Tyrian-Fetherians,</hi> otherwise call'd the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:52570:77"/>
               <hi>Oriflambs</hi> of <hi>Troynovant,</hi> being refresh'd with whole Bowls of <hi>Bacchus</hi>'s <hi>Liquor,</hi> dug up and enter'd their Caves, with that resolution, notwithstanding the stifling smoak proceeding from the Trains of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ental <hi>India</hi> Powder, which the <hi>Vensonpastiggians</hi> had laid to secure themselves, and the <hi>Longing wee monians,</hi> a sort of <hi>Amazons</hi> in <hi>Troynovant,</hi> at deadly feud with the <hi>Vansonpastiggians,</hi> coming in to their Assistance, and carrying away great pieces of the sides, and whole corners of the walls of their Fortifications, the <hi>Vensonpastiggians</hi> were left naked to the fury of their Enemies, and all destroy'd every Mothers Son▪</p>
            <p>Which the <hi>Costardi</hi> seeing, would fain have made their escapes, but being surrounded on every side, they were forc'd to run the same Fate with their Confederates. So that the Victory to his immortal Renown remain'd entire to the Palatine.</p>
            <p>The Fame of this Victory soon spread it self to all the corners of the Wind: But to no body was the news of it so acceptable as to the Princess of <hi>Demonia,</hi> who now believ'd she had espous'd the bravest Champion of the world. And thus ends the first part of this most remarkable Story.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere is lately Published</hi> Quadriennium Jacobi: <hi>Or the History of the Reign of King</hi> James <hi>II. From his first coming to the Crown to his Desertion; Sold by</hi> James Knapton <hi>at the</hi> Crown <hi>in St.</hi> Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52570:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:52570:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:52570:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:52570:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:52570:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:52570:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:52570:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:52570:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:52570:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:52570:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:52570:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:52570:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:52570:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:52570:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:52570:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:52570:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>